Thank you, you read my mind, I was going to close the door.
Alright, hello everybody, welcome back, week three.
So just a couple of notes, the midterm is in three weeks, so May 5th.
If you are in Section 941, you can take it a little early because I set it up so that you can start taking it.
I think it's the Thursday before.
The cutoff, you'll have to make an appointment through the system with the proctoring folks.
But the cutoff will be 9 p.m. on Tuesday, May 5th, which is when we're done with class.
That night we will do the midterm for the first half.
And then we will do class lecture for the second half.
So plan accordingly.
There are limited slots available for the in the classroom.
I'm trying to space you all out because it's a little crowded in here.
If you're at 941, though, so if you are at 941, definitely register because there's a way to say I'm doing it in class.
And if there's no slots left, then please make an appointment.
If you need to make the appointment for a time that is like at the same time as class,
I would do that now, because they do tend to fill up the slots.
So if you want to get on that right away and just make sure you're registered for the midterm
so there's no problems.
One quarter they actually, with all the budget cuts, they tried to cut back on the number
of appointments for exams.
I think they had to restore them because too many students were not getting appointments.
So it's kind of like if you can't run exams, then why are we running a university?
So yeah.
Okay, so there's that.
And then the other thing is, I've said this before, and I will send this out.
I haven't done it yet.
But on Tuesday, May 12th, that night, we will do class remotely on Zoom only.
So for those of you who are used to watching the course online recordings, that week I'll
publish a recording.
for those of you who watch asynchronously.
If you are attending asynchronously,
those of you who are on Zoom,
you will do the same thing you do now.
You will log into Zoom.
Those of you who are normally in the classroom,
because I have to travel on business
so that DePaul will allow me to do the class on Zoom,
so you can attend from home
or wherever you want for that week.
So if you're in Section 901,
That week you can attend class that way.
The other thing I'm going to do that week is I'm going to probably move.
I haven't finalized this, but the Wednesday office hours,
I'm going to move back to probably do a double session on Tuesday.
It'll be the week after the midterm,
so that's usually the week where people want to talk to me.
If you are someone who comes to the classroom
and you can wait after the midterm,
we can go over the midterm.
I'll bring the exams for those of you who want to see your exam on may 19 to
accept her but if you need to know like right away like what I did wrong then we
can do that on on soon and I will make sure to bring all of your exams with me
sorry where I'll be there's Wi-Fi there all right so that's kind of the plan I
will send that details about that out as we get closer. My business trip came
together last week so it was like actually on Tuesday when it all came
together. Lights are booked and everything is set up so I'll get that all figured out.
Okay so that's the housekeeping stuff and then the rest of the quarter will
should be normal, I may have to move another office hours from Wednesday to
another night but we'll figure that out when we get to it.
My schedule gets a little crazy, so sometimes Wednesdays get busy and I have to move you to
them. But I'll always make time outside of office hours, too. If someone really needs to talk,
I'll always try to find a time that works. So just be aware I'm flexible that way.
Okay, any questions about any of that? Detail, exam? Starting next week, we'll probably spend
time in class doing a little more review. Definitely the week before we'll do some review.
There's that study guide that y'all have. Last quarter I did a lot of the study guide questions
I think in the classroom, but we didn't really get through most of it, but that's it seemed to
be okay, it seemed to work out. So I know I've taught this different ways, beginning when I
wasn't sure how much time I needed. The first time I taught it I was actually using the mid-term study
guide every week to go through review stuff but now I've decided to sort of
move that toward the closer things I got so all right so that's it for housekeeping
notes where I'd like to start by going through the quiz from last week just as
a warm-up and then we'll open it up to questions about the homework if there's
anything there I may talk a little bit about that and I've got some new topics
for you all tonight. Seems to be slow. I'm updated on this screen. All right,
so we'll start with the quiz. It's bigger.
Okay, so hopefully this wasn't too hard and hopefully you're able to figure out
to get the REPL to help you if you need to. And don't let it become a crutch though,
you want to start to understand why the answer is what it is.
So we'll talk through this question. This is hopefully pretty easy.
Here's this function f, this x thing here is a type parameter,
and we're getting a parameter, we're getting a value parameter called Xs.
That's a list of whatever type we're using.
And we're returning, we don't know,
because this is using type inference.
So we don't know just by looking at it,
by just looking at this line, we don't know.
We have to look at the rest of it, so.
Okay, so this function looks at the list it got,
and then it does some pattern matching.
And if it gets an empty list, it returns an empty list.
And if it has a head element followed by anything,
thing. This anything is represented by ys here. It returns ys. So what type
does the pattern variable ys have? Does anybody have an idea?
Lists of x.
list of X great so tell us why you think that given that the function has X in
terms of it doesn't list a specific type from the list and you're going you're
doing pattern matching so that's the that's a good rationale for why so so
So you're correct.
The answer is correct, but I was trying to get you explain it.
So your answer Y has to do with why the return type has the type parameter X,
but it's also, as you said, it's a list of X.
So why is it a list of X?
So your answer was half way there because you answered the X part.
But why is it a list?
My assumption was because it was, I don't know if the word iterating would be right,
but it was kind of going through that for the y, ys.
Well, it's not really going through the list,
and what it's doing is it's saying, I'm going to deconstruct the list.
And on the left side, I'm going to have the head element,
and this double colon is what enables us to,
There's actually something called unapply that's implemented on the cons.
This is a cons, basically.
And there's something called, I'm sorry, the unapply is on list.
Sorry, my bad.
It's actually checking to see, like, does this.
Actually, no, maybe it is on there.
I'd have to look.
But that's kind of, like, behind the scenes in how it's implemented.
But what this means when you look at this is it's saying,
I've got a list, and if I have a head element, which I can bind to y.
So that's gonna be of type X.
And on this side I'm gonna have what?
A list of the list.
A list of x.
And if you notice the return value here is ys and
we just said that's type list of x.
Nil can also be of type list x.
So because of that,
the only possible type you can return is list x.
So that's why you have to look at all of it together and
reason about what this type is and what that type is in order to answer that question.
So the reason I'm asking you these questions is to get you thinking, right?
To get you to learn how to think about these patterns, right?
So yes, the answer is list of x.
Okay.
So the next one, we have this algebraic data type.
This is the answers are down here.
We'll get to that in a second.
So we have this algebraic data type and it says for now,
just think of the plus T as a type placeholder that is filled in with a type like int or
a list of something, an instance of options created.
And actually this is later on in the course,
we're gonna talk about what the plus means.
We're not gonna get into that right now, but technically,
when you define an option you need that, and we'll get into why later.
So for now, just think about the t, don't think about the plus, okay?
So, all right.
So what type, if any, does the following Scala expression have?
So here's our algebraic data type.
So we either have a none or we have sum and some value wrapped by the sum thing, right?
And the value is of type t.
That's where this t comes in.
Okay.
So what type does this Scala expression have?
I'll scroll this down a little.
Hopefully keeping, I'm going to have to make it just a tad smaller so we can keep it all
up there.
That'll work.
So what is our type for the Scarlet expression?
I got a list option, list option.
So that would be the second one?
yeah, no way I got that one is by looking at the second line I had a list and none and then some
and then list none or some and none and then some and an int. I was looking for list something,
list something, and then int, and that was the one that had the option.
Yeah, that's a good explanation. So if you look inside here, what you have is you have this sort
of nested structure, right? You have a list of and then this close paren is the end, the last
you know that's the last element over here so you have a list of oh looks like we have
none and sum and then we have this nested thing here okay so it looks like we have a list of
options right so that's your first sort of two layers right so that gives us a couple
i guess yeah a couple different options right and then if we look further we see that when we have a
sum for our option here,
we now have a list of things.
So it looks like we have a list of option of list of,
and there's something else in here,
and using the same sort of approach,
you got sum, none, sum,
and these are ints in here.
So you have option of int in that inner, inner list.
So the inner, inner list is an option of int, right?
And then that's a list.
And then we had an option layer here, and then a list layer there.
So you just have to look at what you see and interpret what's the meaning.
Okay, good.
Question three. The next three questions, I think I actually double checked this.
I'm pretty sure they all use the same combined code. It's like the exact same thing.
So here we have something similar to an option.
But it's a little different.
It's actually quite similar to something
we're going to see a little bit later tonight.
I think it shows up in some of our slides, called an either.
But we'll get to that.
But right now we're thinking about we're computing
a result of some kind.
And either we run into an error, which
is represented by this error case.
Or we have something that is okay.
So the value of our successful computation is going to be of type X.
That's why okay, that has an N that has type X.
And the value of the error, that value contained by the error is going to be some type Y,
and that's going to represent our error.
That could be an exception, that could be some custom error class,
that error enumeration we have, something like that.
We could do that.
Alright, so we need to have this import here so that these things are now in scope.
And then we do this combined function.
So there's a lot of stuff, when I first saw that my eyes popped up.
Because it was late last night, so I was like, alright, what's going on here?
So if you think about it, we're getting a list, so we have to break it down.
We're getting a list of u, and we have a function that, is that a u or a v?
It looks like a u.
The angle of the character made it look like a v for a second.
It's a u.
Yeah, I agree, we're gonna use u.
Okay, I guess it could be a Roman u, if it were a v.
But we have a function that takes a u, something of type u, and
produces this result, which is of type x, y.
So notice we have u, x, and y have to be defined somehow.
Now when we call the function, they'll be fixed at some actual type, right?
But for the sake of the generic implementation of the function,
we can abstract those out, that's what this is doing.
So we have our function, and then ultimately we're going to end up with a result
that either has a list of x, so that would be our x here,
which is our okay type, right?
Or a list of y, which is our errors.
Anytime we get errors, we're going to then do that.
So we look at what the code does.
It looks, it does pattern matching on this list of you.
And it says, well, if I got nil an empty list,
I'm gonna say, I got okay, right.
And nil is perfectly fine as a list of x, right.
So we're gonna have that.
So now we're going to move my mouse.
Now we're gonna deconstruct in the case where we have
a list that has more than one element. We're going to deconstruct it. So we take our head
here and our tail here, right? And we're going to call F whatever function we got and produce
a result. And we're going to put that in a tuple. So that's actually what the syntax
is doing. It's putting this on the first element of a 2 tuple. And then we're going to call
combine on the tail of the list and I'm going to keep passing my function f.
So now if you think about it, as I deconstruct this list, I'm going to invoke this combine
function.
So I'm going to invoke f, which should produce a result first, and I'll hold that, and then
I'll call combine.
And this will just keep pulling elements off the list and going all the way down to nil.
So if you think about it, think about it from the standpoint of the end of the list,
the last element before the end.
Like the end of the list is nil, right?
But the last element, that's not, that's the cons, the last head value.
So you're going to then evaluate, okay, well, what did I get when I process that with the function?
Did I get an error or an okay?
That's what this stuff on the left means.
And then the right side is when I did the combine, did I end up with an error or an okay?
So now to sort of look through that, basically what we're saying is if I got an error this
time and I had an error from before, my error from before is going to have a list.
That's why this is SS by the way, that's just a naming convention.
It's going to have a list.
We're gonna take the single error and we're gonna cons it with the other errors and keep all the errors together and return that.
So if we're dealing with errors and only errors, then we just keep taking our errors and adding them up.
Adding them up meaning like instructing this list.
If we got an okay, but we had errors, we're gonna ignore the okay.
See what happens in this case is we just preserve error SS.
so we just throw away whatever n was if we got an error this time and before when we were doing the
sub list the remaining the tail we got okay this is a little off because it's not wrong it's just
the way it's like space is there normally somebody tried to make that line up nice
But it threw me off because my eyes used to seeing the parentheses there.
But if we got an error and before we had everything OK, we're going to throw away
everything we got before, all the OK stuff, and we're going to just keep the one error
and we're going to put it in a new list with that one element.
And then here, if I got OK in OK, I'm going to keep the new OK value and I'm going to
append it to the other OK Values I had before.
So in English if we wanted to go higher level here, in English what does this function do?
That's a later quiz question.
How would we describe that?
So we're processing a list and we're computing results for each element.
and we're going to keep all of the correct,
all of the successfully processed elements.
And if we ever encounter an error,
then we're going to keep the error.
And once we've got an error,
we're just going to keep accumulating all the errors.
And we'll always, at that point,
throw away all of the good computations.
So that's how I described that.
I look at this code, and I kind of reason about it.
I've got to break it down.
You've got to think about the recursion.
That's the point of this last week's stuff was to get you into this recursive thinking mode with Scala.
Okay, so that's what this function does.
Does everybody follow that?
It's a lot to read.
And would this be an example of the child recursion?
No.
this is not tail recursion.
We haven't covered tail recursion yet, but we will.
If you've read ahead on that,
the reason why it can't be tail recursion is
when I do this, I'm calling the F of V first.
And I'm getting a result.
But then I have to hold that result in memory.
And then I have to call the combined function for the sublist.
And I'm going to keep doing that all the way down.
So I'm always going to have a call stack.
where I'm going to have to hang on to these results.
So it can't be tail recursive for that reason.
If we were doing something where,
so the preview, tail recursion,
in order for something to be tail recursive,
you can't have anything left to do,
any more work to do once the recursive call exits.
So we'll cover that in detail later on.
It's one of my favorite topics actually.
So the answer is, to answer Raven's question,
this is not tell recursive because it has to hang on to this memory.
It can't do this case evaluation until after it's evaluated both of these functions,
and so it has to hang on to whatever the result was.
And then it recurses as it goes down into combine.
And each time it goes down into combine, it's got the previous result is all on the call stack waiting
for the recursive call to exit.
So the quiz question...
Any other questions?
Sorry, not to jump in because I know it's a lot.
Okay.
So what is the output and type of running?
Combine.
And we have list 1, 2, 3.
And then what's this?
Oops, it's jumping around on me.
It's so slow.
It updates on the screen way slower.
And I feel like that's just too small.
so I'm gonna make it just a little bit.
What is this second argument here?
It starts here,
and it goes all the way through this,
up to this last paren.
So what does that, this last paren is just the
closed paren for the invoking method, or the function.
So what is this thing?
I'm modding it by two integers.
That's what it does, sure.
But I'm asking you the whole thing.
Starting here, what does this all mean with this error?
The integer is even printed or error.
Well, it's not really printing.
I mean, .
But you're describing to me what this does.
But what is this?
What is this thing?
What type is it?
Is it a function?
I mean...
Definition.
Say again?
Definition?
Function.
It's a function.
And actually you can see that here.
So here, it's f because it's a function.
It takes a u and it produces a result of xy.
So if you look at this code here, this is our u, because our u is our list.
It's a list of u, right?
So it's a list of ints.
So our u is an int here.
And what we have is a u.
And that produces either an okay or an error, and Scala will look at that and say, well,
if it's an okay or an error, then the most common supertype, or the least common, the
lowest down in the type hierarchy is result.
So it'll match the types that it needs.
So this is a function that, as you were saying, it looks at the value of N that it gets, and
And if it's even, it keeps it, it says OK.
And if it's not even, it's gonna return an error.
So if we run this on one, two, three,
what is the result we get?
You're gonna get an error on one and three.
So yes, and so that means that we're gonna get this
because it's a list of one and three.
Remember it's gonna keep all of the numbers that errored,
all of the elements I should say,
they are, they happen to be numbers,
but all of the elements that errored,
it's gonna keep them in a list,
it's gonna keep constructing that list, right?
So once it got three was the error,
when it was okay for two, it just threw that away
and it kept the three,
And then when it checked one, it appended the one to that list,
the cons that actually technically.
I appended an element to the beginning of the list.
It's kind of weird to say that because we
have an append function, right?
So it's like, I've got to be careful semantics of the words.
But I think the answer is this one here.
So luckily, this is the same code.
I actually was like, this is the same code when I did it myself.
So this time we have, I already verified it's .
Yeah, go ahead.
Quick question, so for the, what was it, number three?
That one threw me off because I thought initially it was error, but
when I had put it in the REPL, I kept getting a new syntax error.
And so then I tried like changing the if to something else and
I kept getting it.
so then I was like, oh, then it has to be the last one.
But that was fine.
And you answered this one?
Yeah.
Well, actually, for the remaining ones, I just kept.
You kept answering?
I kept getting when I would check in the REPL,
the new syntax error.
When I would.
OK.
I'm not sure what the syntax error was.
So when you.
It was saying for the modulo, so then I
tried changing it to just addition or something,
and then I would get another error.
So I was kind of confused on that.
Okay.
I got syntax errors when I was running it
without the build spt file
that said it was supposed to be Scala 3
because I think the default was Scala 2 for me.
So then I would get syntax errors
because enums weren't a thing in Scala 2.
That might be it, question mark?
That's a good point.
Yeah.
So if you happen to be running Scala
and it's Scala 2,
you're not going to be able to do anything
So check that.
So when I put it in the REPL right now, I'm doing it right now, because I was like, let's
see, but notice I'm on Scala 337.
So I'll get it to compile.
Okay.
I'm on three.
I'll ask you after.
Yeah, we can check.
All right.
So then once I have that, if I take this, I mean and you all can do this while you're
studying, it's perfectly fine because I want you to learn how to think through this.
So here's the 1 2 3 version. Oops, I don't know why. Is this? I feel like this is zoomed
or something, even though I'm not running zoom. Maybe it's not zoomed. I don't know
what that is. I must be hitting some key sequence. Anyway, here's the errors 1 and 3, right?
And then for the next question, it's the same code.
I already verified that.
And if I do this one with a 0, 2, and 4, what are we going to get?
Which result?
The first one?
We're getting the first one.
Okay, Dylan, tell me why.
Because they all are okay.
Because they're all okay.
Like they're all going to produce an okay.
And that's because they're all even.
Right?
So if we interpret what that function is in.
There you go.
You got list.
Okay.
Zero, two, four.
So I will put that in here.
And then we'll go to the last question.
And the last question says, it's the same code.
The result type is used to provide either an okay,
indicating successful completion with an associated value or error indicating an
error with an associated value. The combined function applies a function f
to every element of the list where f may either succeed or fail, which description
best matches the behavior of the combined function. So we talked through in the
beginning what this combined function was doing. So which one of these do you
think matches what we were saying, because I stated it probably a little bit differently.
The third option. Which one? The third option. The third option. Returns a collection of all
the errors when any error occurs, even if there are some successes. Yeah, the only thing I feel
bad about this question, like not feel bad, like, but I feel weird about that answer, even though
that's, I believe, the correct answer, it should also say, like, returns a collection. Like,
Otherwise, if none of them fail, it should return a collection of all of the elements that succeed.
Or all the elements.
So it feels a little incomplete to me.
But usually, I get away with questions like that because it's like, what's the best answer?
Right?
So.
All right.
Let's submit this quiz.
And let's see how we did.
And we got five out of five.
So we got all the answers.
So there's a lot of Scala.
in there but this is getting your kind of your mental juices flowing for like what we're
getting into the functional program okay any questions about the quiz
okay what about the homework was there anything on the homework that you
There's a lot of recursion.
Anything?
Anybody online?
Anything from the homework?
Nobody ever asked about the homework.
I didn't do it but I prepared and read the solution.
I've done it before, but I did do it this time.
But I did look through it so I was prepared for any questions you may have.
There are, I guess I'll point out some things with it, maybe worth that.
Let me go over that, so yeah, so.
This is the solution that I give to the greater, so they have,
You know, here's some recursion here for factorial.
So if n is less or equal to one, then one.
Otherwise, n times factorial n minus one.
So that's how you do factorial.
That's a natural recursive way to think about factorial.
Oh yeah, this one was it threw some people off.
Somebody messaged me privately.
Somewhere up on the top it says don't use VAR and then here you have to use VAR and
it actually says it in the directions to use VAR.
So sorry about the confusion if anybody was confused about that.
This is the only place I think in the whole homework where you can use VAR and you need
to use VAR because there's no way this would work on the place.
So what you have here is a for do and it's basically creating a range of 1 to 5.
And then this for do is gonna actually turn into a for each call.
Basically, it's gonna execute this for every element I that you get from one to five.
And so, it'll call fact of one and then factor of two and then factor of three and
then it will just construct this big list.
And the result is this list here because what you're basically doing is,
one to five you're going to compute the factorials of one to five and the
factorials of one to five are one two six twenty four and one two four
In exercise two we're doing Fibonacci so here's a recursive definition of
Fibonacci if you ever I don't think anybody here know Raven you did you took
Data structure is one with me.
We had that whole exercise where we did the terrible Fibonacci,
the one that you let it run for an hour.
And this was two years ago, so I've seen it since that.
But you let it run for an hour and it only
gets through like 54 or something.
And then we have the students convert it to a loop.
And then you can get them all right away
because it's using a loop and it's not redoing computation.
This is the version of Fibonacci that,
notice you're gonna repeat yourself many times right?
You're gonna call Fibonacci n minus one
and then Fibonacci n minus two,
but when you get into n minus two,
you're gonna read, you're gonna redo work.
You're gonna retrace your steps.
You're gonna do it all over again.
And so that's very inefficient.
And that was the whole point of doing that
in Data Structure One.
So sometimes the mathematical definition of something
isn't really the best way to implement it in a computer.
But for the sake of this homework, we were using this version of Fibonacci because we
wanted to get you into the habit of doing recursive thinking in Scala.
There's a lot of like logging versions.
Basically the same thing.
Here's a tail recursive version.
So in this tail recursive version, and again,
we're not gonna cover tail recursive quite yet.
It does some logging.
But if, well,
what we have here is we have this D here,
and that's an accumulator.
When we converted into data structures one,
we convert Fibonacci to a loop.
Like I said, we can always convert while loops
You have to add parameters for things.
So basically what this is going to do is it's going to do this recursively,
but it's never going to repeat itself with the work that it's doing.
So it's keeping this running accumulator here.
And when it gets down to the end, that.
Let's see, d, is that right?
Oh, d is just the depth.
Okay, right.
So it's N-1, I plus J.
So there we go.
That's why.
It's in J.
It's keeping the result.
So anyway, this is another way to do it.
But this one's tail recursive.
That's because if you notice, the recursive call here is the last thing we do.
There's nothing here to add to it or anything.
We do all the computation and then pass it down.
So there's different ways to do this.
This one is kind of an easy one, it's just construct a tuple.
This one, I think the directions, I looked over this, the directions are a little weird
because the array has four things, five things in it, and then the instructions are like
swap array one should return this.
I think, oh no, that's right.
Swap array one should do that.
So it's gonna take the first two elements
and swap them and then return them as a tuple.
This is just getting you dealing with these sum types here.
And sum, done recursively.
So this is very logical,
just thinking through how to do stuff recursively in Scala.
There is a min, so this is similar to sum, it's min.
And then there's this tree thing, which has you convert trees to list representations
of the data that's in the tree, just to give you some more experience with recursion.
And this upto thing which produces a list in reverse, I guess.
It's like opto backwards.
Somebody made this up.
And then, oh, the correct unique, so this one was you had to write the contract.
There's really nothing too exciting here.
I don't remember what the bug actually is.
Did anybody find what the bug was?
I think it was the duplicate.
It would only catch it if it was consecutive.
Like, for that LSIF.
Okay.
Yeah, yeah, yeah.
Got it.
Yep.
So you weren't supposed to fix the bug.
You were just supposed to write the contract.
Okay, cool.
So that's our homework two.
Any questions?
Cool. Well, we got some new stuff tonight then. We'll get into it.
I'll need, I'll close homework 2.
I'm going to keep homework 1 because at one point in tonight's lecture, we're going to
jump back to a question from first homework.
Let's see which one is this.
I got it.
That's a solution.
I need one.
I need to close one of these.
So not that one.
Oh, I want to solution that's right.
I don't need an extra clutter on my desk.
I'm doing this.
All right.
Cool.
So if we go into, so our first topic today is about strict and non-strict evaluation.
So this is a way to start defining something that we kind of are already familiar with,
but we just don't think about it or talk about it in these terms until you get to studying
programming languages. So our learning objectives here, how much of an
expression should be evaluated when computing a result. We're going to perform
expression evaluation and perform function calls and function argument
evaluations. We're going to take a deep dive into some low-level building blocks
of our programming. So we have this idea of strict versus non strict. So what
is a strict construct.
The easiest way to think about this
is you ask yourself,
if I look at some code,
what do I have to evaluate
in order to make that code work?
So we think about the first example
under strict arithmetic operators.
So we have some expression like x plus y.
I don't like this pen.
I'm going to switch the color.
I worked with a guy once, he used to throw him in the garbage can.
Right away.
We were on the room.
I was like, whoa, that was violent.
I guess this is a good head.
Go ahead.
I know.
That's why I'm putting it over here.
I'm just an adjunct.
I don't feel like I can just throw these things out.
Maybe I should bring you into somewhere and be like, this is brutal.
All right.
So if we have some expression x plus y, and actually,
So that's, just to make it interesting, let's do x minus y plus w plus z.
Oh, I don't want to use plus, I want to use times.
Okay.
So before I can do this, I have to do this and I have to do this.
So that is why we say that arithmetic operators plus minus are strict.
They're strict because we have to evaluate each operand in order to do the operation.
Comparison operators are the same.
So if you have, instead of plus here, you have less than, you're going to get a boolean, right?
But you have to do this and do this before you can know whether it's less than or not, right?
Okay.
Bitwise operators, that's where you're taking the bits for numeric values
and doing ors or ands or Xors bitwise.
So you line up the bits that then you divide.
Function calls.
So normally in most of the languages that we use,
when we're like Java, C, C++, Scala so far,
the stuff we've done, when we call a function,
so here we're going to have, they have X and Y,
And like, let's say we've got a plus b comma c plus d.
Well, in order for us to call this function,
we have to actually execute this and do this evaluation
and get the result and then pass it.
And same here, right?
So that's what makes it strict.
That's why we call it strict, because you have to evaluate.
You have to go down and do all this.
By contrast, we have things that are non strict.
So we already are familiar with some of these.
I call it short circuit evaluation, because like C, and C++, and Java,
which I learned first.
If you have this expression here, e one and e two.
This is a Boolean.
and if E1 evaluates to false, we don't bother evaluating E2.
That's the way the languages work.
So this is non-strict in E2 but strict in E1 because you have to evaluate.
You evaluate this one, and then you might evaluate this, and you might not.
So this one is non-strict.
For Boolean-or, same idea.
So, if you get a false here, you have to evaluate this.
But if you get a true here, our languages will most of the time that we,
the languages we use aren't going to bother to evaluate this because if this one is true,
the whole expression is true.
So that's non-strict.
Another one that we don't think about much but if we think about if, then, else.
We have if e1, then e2, else e3.
So if E1 evaluates to true, we have to evaluate E2.
If E1 evaluates to false, we have to evaluate E3,
but we don't evaluate the other one, right?
So we're always evaluating E1, so that's strict.
And then E2 and E3, we may or may not evaluate,
so they are non-strict.
So simple definitions of something we've already seen,
We just didn't know that that was what we call it.
So here's a conditional expression.
If e1, then e2, else e3.
So we evaluate e1.
If true, then evaluate e2, else.
I said all this on the previous slide because I forgot.
So, yeah, so here we have if, then, else.
So if we were to evaluate both of these all the time,
we would get something we wouldn't expect.
We would actually print all of this,
even though we only want to print one.
Does that make sense?
So in a conditional statement, like this one in c,
We're gonna either return one, or we're gonna return n times factorial n minus one,
but never both of these when evaluating that expression.
So here's our ternary operator again.
So conditional expression must be non strict, cuz otherwise,
in this case, if this were strict, we would have a non terminating recursion.
So if you think about it, so if n is less than or equal 1, 1 else, or
n times .
So this would actually keep going.
And you would always evaluate this so when you get down to 1, you won't stop,
you'll keep subtracting 1, and you'll keep executing.
So that's why this has to be non-strict.
So back to our function calls.
Function calls are going to be strict.
So what happens here?
So we print i and then we call f.
We pass this Boolean value.
Right, so we evaluate this.
And then we pass this expression, sorry,
We pass this, yeah, we pass an expression.
We evaluate this expression.
It will actually do the print line here.
And because this is strict, it will do the print line.
And it will, the print line actually returns a unit.
So remember I said everything in Scala is an expression.
And that means that when we evaluate that expression, we get a value.
And in this case, the value is side effected and it produced a unit,
which is kind of a void placeholder.
Like, think of it that way.
But this will actually print even and then pass the unit that results here,
and then print odd and then pass the unit that results here.
They're the same thing, but this will say, well, if b, then, and then there's no effect.
You did all the printing before.
Does that make sense?
I would encourage you to throw that in the REPL and watch it print both.
So both even and odd are printed every time f is in vote.
That's useless.
That's not really what we want.
So Scala has this feature. It's called callByName. And what we're doing here is we're actually
passing an expression that will be evaluated when and if it's needed. So that's with this
little arrow here. We add that. So before we just had t, colon, unit, we're adding this
arrow. So when we add this arrow, we're passing an expression and here we're also passing
an expression. They're named t and f here because true false, right, that's the reason
for the names. These are called thunks. Why are they called thunks? Somebody always asks
me that, so I may as well just throw the question out. They are called thunks because it's like
I thought of it, but I didn't think it all the way through. I think that's what that
is like I never read that anywhere I think I think why are they called thunks
but we in computer science when we say the word thunk we're talking about this
so you're building up you have some sort of expression that remains on
evaluating and you evaluate it when you need it so we pass something you thought
of all right so if we do this now we'll actually get the result we want if we
call f for each value of i from 0 to 10 will get only one apiece, because it will only
need to evaluate either t for f. So it's basically deferred execution. That's another way to
say it. It's deferred. So, strict evaluation is going to evaluate all operands to determine
the value of an expression. So this is going to be our arithmetic operators,
our function arguments. Non-strict is going to evaluate only necessary
operands to determine values. Conditional expression, short-circuit
evaluation of Boolean expressions... and it doesn't have called-by-name on there, but it probably should.
Oh there it is. Well they say thunx, which is the more technical formal term.
Request explicit non-strict evaluation of function arguments.
So Scala has support for that.
Our other languages do not.
Well, Java may have it in Lambdas now,
but I never was a Java, professional Java developer
after I added languages.
I was using Scala, so it was .
OK, so that's strictness versus non-strictness.
So it's not a difficult concept.
You're already familiar with it.
I just didn't have the language to describe it.
All right.
So now we're going to get into some more functional stuff.
And this one is a long slide deck.
So we'll find a logical place to stop and do our work.
My typical algorithm is if there's like thirty-five slides, then there's seventy minutes and
time.
That's how I know how much material is.
Took me a little while to figure that out with this material.
Because each class is different.
Okay, so we're going to talk about some stuff with lists.
So we're going to think about what are common ways of processing collections functionally.
So instead of just like old fashioned iteration like we're used to doing in C and Java,
we're going to start to think about how can we be more functional in our programming.
We're going to express and interpret collections processing in a functional style.
So we're going to look at collections, we're going to figure out how to process them in
a style that's different than what we're used to doing.
We're going to compare where the state of computation lives when we're doing iteration
versus recursion.
We're going to express and interpret collections processing
with list comprehension.
So I also call these four comprehensions.
We were talking about those before.
Actually, this is why I'm going to jump back to last week's homework
because there's something in there that will become crystal clear
when we talk about this topic in this set of slides.
We're also going to infer result types of four comprehensions.
We're going to figure out what, when looking at a four comprehension,
what the result type is based on what we see and figure how to do that.
So, if we go back to high school and
we have a function like this f of n equals 2n,
or f of n equals n times 2.
So here's our function, f of n equals 2 plus 2 plus 2 end times.
So our theorem is, for all natural numbers, n.
F of n is n times 2.
And in high school, we learned how to prove this.
And we do this proof by induction.
So we start by saying, well, let's verify this is true for f of 0.
So if we have f of 0, and we do this n times 0 times, we get 0.
0. So f of 0 is 2 times 0, 0. So that's our base case. Now we have this induction hypothesis,
which says, assume this theorem is true for f of n minus 1. I learned it f of n, and then
you do, I did f of k actually, and then f of k plus 1, but that doesn't matter. You assume
it's true for something. So f of n minus one is going to be n minus one times two. We assume
that's true. And then we have to prove that f of n is equal to, yeah, f of n is equal
to n times two. And the way you do that is you actually show like all of the steps, right?
So we did that.
But what we can do now is we can express this in a program because this is a recursive definition.
So if we take that recursive definition and we implement the idea of the proof in Scala as a recursive function,
here's f of n.
If we have 0, we have, if we get 0, we return 0.
And if we get n, we return f of n minus 1 plus 2.
So, here's our nth two, because this is all of our n minus 1 twos.
Right? So, we can do that. OK.
So programs are proofs.
This is called the Curry-Howard correspondence.
So, this is not something I talk about regularly.
I had to look it up, but basically what it is is
you can click here, and it'll take you over to Wikipedia,
and, in programming language theory and proof theory,
The Curry Howard correspondence is a direct relationship between computer programs and
math algorithms.
So you can kind of read up on this.
It's probably named after Haskell Curry, who is a famous computer science guy.
I don't know who this is.
Oh, William Howard.
William Alvin Howard.
Haskell Curry, I know because he created the Haskell program.
Or it's named after him.
I don't know if he created it.
I'm not sure.
So if we have this exercise here where we're gonna print every element of the list,
we wanna express this in a functional style using pattern matching.
So how would we do it?
What do we do with pattern matching?
What's the pattern we use?
You always start with the thing, the list thing, right?
So let me say excess match.
And if we have an empty list, we're going to produce unit.
And if we have, right now this is kind of a contrived, right?
Because we're not really doing anything.
It's returning unit, right?
We're going to just call print list, oh, sorry.
If we get nil, we're going to do nothing.
If we have y const with some tail, we're going to call print list on y,
so we did nothing with y here.
So we didn't actually print anything, so that's not going to actually do the printing, but we can add that.
There, we add the print line, right?
Notice our return type here is unit, matches that.
Print line, remember everything's an expression, so since this has a side effect and doesn't give us a value back,
the value we get back is unit.
So this has type unit, this has type unit, and because this is a sequence,
of expressions, this is the value for this case that's returned.
Remember, each case is a function, right?
So this is a, we're invoking this function and we're getting back unit,
we're invoking this function that takes this and getting back unit.
So that's why there's unit there, okay.
So we're visiting the elements by deconstructing the list.
So if we want to format every element before printing, we can change the code.
So all I did here is print line Y just prints the integer value.
Print line S, this is that string interpolation thing I showed you.
So S will splice the value of Y in here.
So we have Y equals and then the value of Y.
So that's what that will do.
So now we're going to generalize the idea of processing every element.
So we go back one slide.
Notice there's on print list there's only one parameter, right?
It's the list.
Now we have two parameters.
We have the list and we have F, which takes an int and produces a unit.
I would like to pronounce this error produces.
So f takes an int and produces a unit.
Okay, so we do our pattern match like before.
We get nil, we return nothing.
There's nothing to do.
There's nothing to print, so there's nothing to do.
If we get y followed by some tail,
then we invoke f to get the unit back,
and f will do some something, some side effect, right?
In this case, we're passing print line here.
So print line can take an int and return a unit.
Perfectly fine.
So then we'll call forEach, which is we've renamed this function forEach, right?
We've also generalized it because we're no longer doing the,
we don't know about the printing here.
That's why we rename this forEach.
And then we'll just recurse and call this on the tail,
passing that function again.
So we'll keep invoking f.
So now, we will customize with a changed function argument.
So here, the difference now is instead of print line, we're just calling print y, which
is our own function.
That takes our y and calls print line.
This is with our formatting that we added.
So we can do that here, like that.
And now we're going to generalize the type of the list so that if we compare against
previous slide, we had list of int, and our f was taking an int and producing a unit.
Now we have a list of x, where x is this abstracted out type.
And we're taking an x and doing some side effect, and getting the unit.
So same structure here, but now we have this print length function, which instead of what
we were printing before, we're printing something different.
We're now printing the length of the lists that are contained in here.
So we're no longer using it here.
Now we can use whatever type we want.
We can use it with it, but in this case, we're using it with a list of lists of
it.
We have this nested list.
So if we say print length on this, what do we get, by the way?
The length of each list.
Right, so what are the actual lengths?
Three, zero, two.
Right, it's gonna print three, zero, two.
Everybody see, three, zero, two.
And that's because we're always printing the length here.
Now, we're gonna generalize this a little bit more
by using a lambda expression.
So well, actually not generally.
We're gonna just invoke it differently,
I guess is better.
So in this case, what we'll do
is we'll get rid of that print-length that we had up here
and we'll just inline it down here.
So here we take a list events
and we just call print-line on the link.
So we've just moved it down here.
Now,
We'll take this idea further a little bit.
So we're gonna use the, in this case, we're using the built-in list class which
has a for each method.
So we have this named method print and print x is just gonna call print line on it.
So if I say xs4each print, it will just print the element.
Lambda expression, you can, instead of calling for each with the named method print,
now you can call for each with this inlined method, or I should call that a function,
actually because you're passing a function.
It's not going to do that.
So there's our inlined.
And now since all we're doing is print line, we can actually, well, we can drop the type parameter.
So that's because Scala can infer this, in this case.
It knows that Xs contains a list of ints.
So, and this is not really a great example.
But before we had this, we bound the type to int.
We indicated that.
Here the compiler figured it out based on the types that are in Xs, whatever they are.
It doesn't matter for print line.
you can print line anything, right.
Anything that's a two-string because it will automatically be all two-string.
But now, this is even redundant.
So I can convert this to this anonymous intermediate function.
I'm sorry I can convert this to this, I forget what it's called.
Might be a single abstract method.
That's a technical term that you don't need to know.
But what this is saying is I can call for each.
I'm going to pass print line itself as a function that takes an int and produces a unit.
So I don't have to actually take the x and write my own function.
I can actually just pass the function.
In JavaScript, it's called anonymous function.
It's called anonymous function in JavaScript?
Yes.
Cool.
So, this anonymous intermediate function here is unnecessary.
So we can just do this.
So I said backwards the first time, that's why I corrected myself.
Okay, so types and functions parameters.
So this capital X here is a type parameter.
So that appears here in Scala after the name of the method.
Type parameters are gonna be show up in square brackets.
And the value parameters will show up in these round brackets.
I don't call those brackets, I call those parentheses.
So many of us call them brackets.
The value parameters, why these are value parameters,
these are the values you pass.
And the types occur before.
Values.
X types before values.
So, types before values.
That's what that means.
I don't think about it that way, but that's because I go too fast.
This F parameter is actually a function type.
So that's why I in the place I was asking all that, what is that?
So that's a function type.
It takes an X and produces a unit.
And anything that complies with that type can be used.
So let's talk a little bit about recursion.
So when we're working with C and Java, we're doing mostly, before lambdas, we're doing
mostly iteration.
We have a collection of data, we're iterating over it.
In fact, for all of Data Searchers 1, I discourage lambdas from my class because I'm trying
to get you to go really low level and think about what's going on, like, when we're processing
So we're starting now to abstract out into functional programming.
So functional programming is going to favor immutable data and iteration using Recursion.
So this is actually an important point.
We can get away with a lot because we have immutable data.
We don't change our lists around.
We don't change the values that are stored in lists.
And we can trust that because they're immutable there's like things that we can just assume
about lists.
There are immutable versions of collections in Scala, but I don't even use them in production
code.
It doesn't arise.
It could be, but in the work item I don't.
Recursion requires efficient method calls.
So think about the state of computation.
When we're doing imperative or just think about like a loop that's summing up all the
elements like in a list, like a job, well, we have to have some variable that we're
using to store the accumulated sum as we go through the list, right?
So we call these global, not because they're global, but they're global to every element
of the collection and we keep updating it, right?
and that's why we need mutability,
because we have to update some data in memory.
With recursion, we store the state of the computation
in our arguments to recursive calls.
Now, that's not necessarily always the case
if you're not doing tail recursion.
If you're doing non-tail recursion,
you might store arguments,
store comp parts of the computation in the call stack,
But for what we like to do in functional programming,
as we move toward more functional implementations
of collections processing, we're going
to think about the arguments are actually
in the recursive column.
So here's a classic imperative implementation
of computing the length of the list.
So we have our length function.
We've got a list of ints.
So, returning an int, that's gonna represent the length.
We're then going to create a length variable
that contains zero to begin with,
and it's a var so we can update it,
so that's mutability.
Then we're gonna have a while loop, right?
We're gonna say, well, I'm not at the end of the list.
This is classic like linked list processing
from data structures one, right?
It's a little different because we've got this tail thing,
but in data structures one, we had like a next pointer,
and when the next pointer was nulled,
and we knew we were done.
Here when we get to nil, we know we're done.
So that's the parallel analog to what we did there.
But in Scala we can iterate through the list like this,
keep updating our length by adding one to it
until we get to the end, and then we return length.
Remember you don't need the word return,
just the last expression is the return value.
So we updated our length as we walked through the list.
So a recursive version of this with pattern matching,
this one actually has the one plus here.
So, touching on that tail recursive topic that we'll do another week.
We have to store this one here somewhere in the computer in the call stack while
the length function is recursively called and executes, and
is gonna go all the way down through the entire list
and it's gonna have one plus, one plus, one plus,
all the way out right, as it goes down.
Notice here we use a whatever, we don't care.
Because we don't care what the value is,
we just are counting that the element exists.
So, we're just adding one for that.
If it were sum, we would need that
but we're not doing sum.
Okay, so this is what the computation looks like
with our imperative iteration.
So when we start off, we have our current list.
Remember in that first code, block the code,
we did this the old Java way,
and as we compute, we start off with our length equal to 0.
And our length is going to update,
so we'll pull that first element off,
and then we'll add 1.
And then we'll pull the next element off,
and we'll add 2.
We'll add one to it to get two.
And then we get down to the end here,
we pull this last element off,
and we add one to our length, and then we return it.
So the state of our computation
is in these mutable variables.
In this case, just one mutable variable.
That's the state of our computation, it's stored there.
Let's look at what happens with our recursive iteration.
So in our recursive iteration,
we do this, and we say,
okay, we're gonna do one plus the tail.
We're going to 1 plus length of the tail.
And then 1 plus 1 plus the length of the tail.
And then 1 plus 1 plus 1 plus the length of the tail.
And now we're going to get length of nil, which is going to give us 0.
And then we'll keep going.
So 1 plus 0 gives us 1.
And now we're going to do this next evaluation.
1 plus 1 will give us 2.
and now we're going to have one plus two
and now we're going to get three.
So in this case, the state of our computation
is actually in the expression
and not this meanable variable in the form.
So we've kind of moved the state of the computation
from this low-level concept of being in the memory,
even though we're still using memory, obviously,
but we're letting the programming language
control that more by putting in the expression.
So let's look at lists, and there are two methods here where the slide is titled map
so that's the stuff on the right.
But we have a foreach over here on the left, so notice foreach takes a type parameter x
and a list of x and then it's got an f that takes an x and produces a unit.
We've seen this a little bit before.
The final result of calling foreach is going to be a unit.
So we'll then deconstruct the list, we look at Xs.
If we get nil, that's going to return unit, do nothing and return unit.
If we get something else, we're going to call f on the head of that something else,
and then we're going to recursively for each with the tail.
And of course we have to keep passing the function down, so
it always has access to that.
So the result here is unit and there's no actual result collected.
So this is great for side effects like printing and stuff.
Map, on the other hand, is going to visit and transform every element.
So if we look at this, now we have two type parameters.
So instead of unit, we now have a list of y coming back.
And if we start with a list of x, of type x, and for each element,
we're gonna convert that element from a type x to a type y, to some value of type y.
Then when we deconstruct the list, if we get nil, of course, we have an empty list.
But if we have something else, we're going to convert the x to a y by calling the function.
And then we're going to cons it with the result of calling map on the tail of the list.
That's what's going on here.
And so, at a high level,
you're transforming each element,
list of x, that's in this list of x to a list of y.
Okay?
So this is kind of like one of the first fun,
we started talking about recursion before.
Now, we're looking, we're doing recursion,
but we're also now starting to formalize
collections processing, we're processing the elements here,
we're using this function and we're letting this map function do the heavy lifting.
Instead of us having to iterate and do it all ourselves.
So the result here is this list of y.
It's a transformed copy.
So if we call map on this list of 11, 21, 31.
And this thing here is going to take a y and
And it's going to say x equals string concatenate with
a two string version of this y.
You're going to produce strings, right?
So if I do this, my result is a list of strings.
And if I start, sorry, if I call this,
I get back this list of three strings, x equals 11, x equals 21, x equals 31.
So I already see that, so that's what map is doing.
Built-in, so I can do it this way.
Right, built-in just means that the map function is actually implemented
on the list type.
So both const and nil will have an implementation of map.
Or it might just be in the list type.
So here's some examples.
So, if I want to increment each value in a list,
here's my list of just one, two, three, four.
And here's my function.
I'm calling map, sorry.
And I'm passing the function.
And this underscore is like a don't care or whatever.
Students last quarter wanted to call it whatever,
because it's actually like the argument is actually used
to do the addition.
So they felt that whatever was a better name,
but most of the time we just call it a don't care,
but you can think of it as either way.
So what happens when I call this,
if I have a list of one two three four
and I map it using the function
where I do an increment by one,
then I get list of two, three, four, five.
Here's one example where I take the length
of the inner lists.
So I have a list of lists, and here I have 3, 0, 2.
Again, this is that same example we saw before.
And if I map over the length, then I'm going to convert each of these
lists to the length of those lists.
And the result will be in a list of course, because the result will always
be the same as the outer type with map.
Length of strings. So if I have a list of strings,
I take a list of these three strings.
Hi, it's me. And I map over the length. I'm going to get two,
four, and two because of the length of those strings.
So here's our next one.
Filter. So we just did map. We did for each. We did map.
Remember the difference is that for each
is going to do something for each element,
but not return anything other than a unit,
which is just an expression.
It's a type that just indicates
that there's nothing to return.
Map is going to actually, for a list,
it's going to return a list.
So we'll do these examples.
So now we're going to do a new one, filter.
So here, this is slightly different.
I only have one type parameter, X.
I have my list of X, like before.
But this time, I have a predicate function.
And the predicate function simply takes an element of whatever type we are using
and determines whether some predicate is true.
Whether some expression is true.
So here, the way this is implemented, if I have nil, of course,
the result is nil. Here I have if I have something else, so remember we said
they'll match on the first case. Right? Well this extra if here makes these two
things different. So here if I have something else, if f of y so if this
function returns true for this element this first element, then I'm going to
return y cons with the result of calling filter on the rest of the list. And if
If not, so if f of y returns false we'll drop to this case.
Of course I don't care about what this first value was here, this y.
So I'll say, well I won't do this consing here.
I'll just call filter.
And remember I'm getting a list back, so I get a list back, I cons.
Here I get a list back and I don't cons.
So here's the example in my z's I have zero to seven.
list, this 0 to 7, by the way, produces a range, which is a different type in Scala,
so that's why we have to call two lists to make it work with lists.
So then I'm saying filter, and I'm saying I want to filter,
and I want the elements that are not divisible by 3.
So if I do that, I should lose 6,
sorry, 3 and 6 in that order. I should lose 3 and 6, so my result is
1, 2, 4, 5, 7, so that's what I would expect.
Because we're keeping the ones that are not visible by three.
So it's filtering them out, right?
They also have to filter not, by the way, so that just reverses the condition.
Okay, so list and set comprehensions.
So these are like more mathematical ideas here.
So a set comprehension,
expression, this expression here in mathematical language.
You have an M, you have a tuple M and N, sorry, M paired with N,
where M is an element of zero to ten and N is an element of zero to ten.
And M is less than or equal to M.
So this is a mathematical expression.
You're imposing these constraints on these things.
So you say that this is the set of all tuples, M and N,
that m is in zero to 10, n is in zero to 10, and the value of m is at most the value of n.
So in many programming languages, we have these list comprehensions. The first one was,
I guess, let's click the links to, I didn't do that... So Wikipedia has a syntactic construct
in some programming languages for creating a list based on existing lists.
My college professor said that LISP, which is a programming language that is somewhat
functional, it stands for list processing, he said it tends to be AHA perfect.
Dr. Gamer, it's crazy.
I still see him sometimes.
His wife usually makes him go antiquing, so when I go up to town, it was my college,
He's almost never available, but I told him I'm teaching this stuff now, so you've got to chuckle all that,
because he remembers me when I was younger than all of you.
So learning this stuff.
But, so, right, so there's this other language called Settle, set language.
I don't even really know much about it.
It's a very high-level programming language.
So most of the languages we deal with, by the way, are called high-level languages.
And that's different from higher-order programming, which is what we do with functional programming.
The reason the term high-level language has to do with the fact that programming used to be sitting down and writing hexadecimal codes.
That's what programmers did in the 1950s, and then they came up with compilers and higher-level languages.
So when they say very high-level language, I started to chuckle because I was like, oh, it must be higher than just what we're used to.
So settle.
Haskell.
So in Haskell you can do this, which is basically exactly what we're doing here in this mathematical language.
It's an Ascii version, or Unicode.
Scala, we can do it this way.
So we're using this for comprehension to express a list comprehension.
So for M in 0 to 10, N in 0 to 10, if M is less than or equal to N, yield MN.
So this actually imposes that condition.
So you can do this in Scala.
Do a Python, there is a Python.
Do in JavaScript.
So, here's our for comprehension.
So.
When we do this, so that's right.
When we when we do this, so that's right,
this, and this are the same and I'll explain.
So here this is where map,
we're calling map and this is the function where we take whatever the element x is,
and we say x, this is a string, x equals.
And then we're adding x to that string.
So x equals, and we're just placing that in there.
Not really, it's a concatenating type.
If we use for yield, then we're doing the same thing.
So, this is actually syntactic sugar for that.
When I say syntactic sugar, it's easier to read.
What the Scala compiler does though, is when I do this,
it's looking for a map function on this thing.
And if it doesn't find one, so whatever that is,
if it's, it could be,
it actually could be something other than a list,
We do it all the time with sets, we do it with, that's what the previous slide had set language.
We do it with options as well, which we'll cover later.
You can do it on ethers, you can do it on so many different things,
but there has to be a map for this for to work.
And the same thing for for each.
So when we have for each and we pass this, this takes,
this function takes an x of type whatever excesses, whatever is contained by this,
And Printline, of course, produces a unit because it just prints and doesn't return anything except the unit.
The for-do version of this, so this is for-yield, this is for-do, and this is syntactic sugar for that.
So the compiler, when it sees this, looks for a for-each implementation on the collection.
So that's why I use the term for comprehension and not for loop here, because you're not really implemented like Java.
When you have for, the compiler constructs something different.
In this case, it converts it and then constructs it.
Here's the filter.
So if we have filter, this is like our example before.
Well, what we get is this.
We can do this.
syntactic sugar, easier to read, for Z and Zs if Z mod 3 is not equal to 0, yield c.
So that's the same as that.
By the way, this expression here, you don't need to bind to type Z.
That's why my students wanted to call it whatever, because it's actually used in this function.
It don't care, whatever.
So, if we have nested methods, so nested methods we have,
first we're filtering and then we're calling map on the filtered result, right?
So first we filter out the things divisible by three and
then we map to the stringified z equals, and then the value, right?
So you can do that with four comprehension.
so you would have 4z and z's. If z mod 3 is not equal to zero, yield that,
so you can nest them this way. So again, syntactic sugar.
I think we will break here and pick this up after the break, so come back at 7.30.
Haaag.
Thank you.
okay
wow that's amazing
Yeah.
Thank you.
I'm going to go back to the next one.
All right.
...
I'm going to do the best.
Sure.
All right.
Okay.
So, let's go.
Can you show you what I had got?
Sure.
Just that picture?
Am I going crazy?
Show me the referal.
Oh, yeah, let's go higher,
because you can set that computer.
This one must be.
And I should have bombed my first inclination, but it kept doing that.
So it's like, oh, I must be.
It was the one with the result, right?
Yeah.
Yeah, I kept getting this so then I tried with just like different inputs to see and
then it would, but it implies that there's.
I looked it up and I was like yeah, I'm going to write one and everything but it kept doing
that.
You go back in what is this, VS code?
Go back to the project and show me the build.svm.
Because that's telling me something.
There's something I'm not familiar with from that message.
New syntax required and undo and control expressions.
Oh.
Okay.
I know what this is.
No, no, no.
You didn't mess up.
So, okay.
So, first of all, you're running from the homework.
Okay, and you're calling sbt, which is gonna load up all the configuration in this build.sbt
And that's gonna take on this new syntax, which is gonna require this this particular expression
If you were to paste it into the repl without that
So if you I don't know if you have it set up on the command line
Yeah, I did and then I was like oh I can just so I had been doing you you if you set it up on the command line
And just call Scala and go in there and paste it. It would work if the problem is that
is that, this is Scala2 syntax,
and this new syntax requires that.
That's all it is.
It's a syntax issue.
Oh, okay.
I thought it was weird that it wouldn't,
and I was like, I literally don't know,
but I kept checking, and I was like,
no, then it must be that option, but okay.
Okay, yeah, I can see how, right.
But you gotta learn to read the error message, right?
So whenever you get the compiler tells you something like this,
you should say to yourself, oh, there's
some compiler option that is being used.
It's not a C option.
And that's true of any language, really.
Compiler errors, if they're good,
I'll tell you things like that.
So because I have a ton of experience,
I was like, oh, I know what that is.
Go see what that is.
And then here's the comment right there tells me what it is.
Otherwise I would've googled that.
I would've been like, what does that option do?
I think I was like reading, because when I looked it up, yeah.
So what I would say, like when doing the quizzes and stuff, try not to do it from the homework bubble.
And do it from the regular command line.
That way you'll get a better answer.
Because for some reason, and I didn't set that up on there, but I think it's because we're trying to get students to write Scholar 3.
But the course was originally developed when it was still Scholar 2.
so I could probably fix the syntax of the quiz.
Oh, okay.
I'll probably do that.
So this group is finding all of these little nitpicky things,
which is great because I make notes about them and then fix.
Just today I saw a typo, just an English word type,
just missing a letter.
I was lecturing so I don't have time to fix it, but
I'm going to make a note of it.
The next video was to have a special edition of The American Pronunciation Guide Presents
to know how to show the list of products.
This is a product that I've been using this product.
So, I don't know why it's a product.
I don't know why it's a product that I'm using this product.
It's the product that I'm using.
I don't know why it's not.
We're going to show you how to show it.
We're going to have to go to the next step.
You want to go to the next step?
If you want to go to the next step,
we'll have to go to the next step.
We're going to have to go to the next step.
So, that's it.
I wanted to make a bag of straws.
I don't know why I had to use any of the straws.
I'll take a break.
I'll go with the straws.
You can't use the straws.
I'm going to use the straws.
I'm going to use the straws to make a bag.
I'm going to use them for straws.
I will use the straws.
I'm going to use the straws to make a bag of straws.
I don't know why it's not even a straws.
So I saw some examples about visual messages about the micand
and the delta-hawkins.
So, are there really the underlying conditions in Scala or ?
Oh, they're actually implemented in Scala.
Yeah.
Because I think maybe the recursive functions are more like a cost.
Well, sure, but in Scala, we generally aren't worried about that.
So we wouldn't use it for like high-performance computing.
Yeah.
Why?
Why is that?
Well, because Scala is going to construct objects.
I mean, the JVM has like, if you construct your objects
and the lifetime of the object is not too long,
it won't be promoted.
I don't know how much you know about the Java memory model,
but there's like the survivor spaces and there's like the old
JED, I think these have different names for them.
But there are these different, like so on the heap,
the objects are all sitting up there in the keep.
And as your program executes, if the object lives long enough,
it gets moved from one location to another.
The garbage collector does that.
And that's called moving it from Eden.
These are the old terms.
I don't know if they call it anymore.
But Eden was where when you say new, you get it on Eden.
And then if it goes away fast, it doesn't need to move it
around, but it moves it between these survivor spaces
And eventually after two or three times, it moves it into old gen.
And old gen used to, I don't think it any dozen more,
it used to require full garbage collection.
So I actually worked at a financial exchange where we implemented stuff in Java 25 years ago,
and we learned about this, about the survivor spaces and about the memory model,
and how to make your object lifetime short,
so that the garbage collector did the stock all the trading.
But for a high-performance application,
Scala isn't going to be the best choice
because it's going to be slower than even Java would be.
So you're going to probably pick a language like Rust, or C,
or something that's a little bit more
for something more safer?
it's memory safe.
Yeah, it's memory safe.
But even though you want your application to perform,
you don't need it to perform as fast as,
like you would if you were doing high performance training.
So, that's, sure.
So we don't care in Scala.
So recursion, yes, it takes, it's more CPU cycles,
but for the applications we use Scala for,
it wouldn't matter.
That's like picking the right language for the problem.
Yes, exactly.
Actually I've worked for five years as a firm and I know JavaScript and JavaScript as a
computer language and it doesn't need to be very performant.
Performant, yeah.
Because the browser is fast enough.
Yes.
Right.
I will make a look at the bag of a cup.
It is not too easy to make a cup of coffee.
It is perfect for the cup of coffee.
It is perfect for the cup.
All right, so we're talking about four comprehensions.
We did our map, our for each, and we showed you the syntactic sugar for yield and for
do, and then we had, it's not advancing.
There we go.
We have filter, and that's how we use four comprehensions to do filters.
And then we have these nested methods here.
So we have this filter and then a map.
So here's the examples we, oh, we saw some examples before, but
this is kind of where we stopped.
So if I take this list of lists, and I have this for expression here.
Sorry, I got mad at myself.
So here we have multiple iterators.
So what this is doing is it's saying for every element in x, s, s.
And I'm gonna take every element in that and then I'm going to do something with x.
So here what I'm doing is I'm producing a list and
I'm gonna have each value of the inner list followed by the length of that list.
So since the first one, you see how this is 11, 21, 31, that's why we get 11, 21, 31 here.
And that's in a list of three so we're always gonna get three.
And then we're also getting this 41 and 51 with the Lists' length of 2.
So it's actually going on here, there's another function called flatMap, I think it shows
up later in the slides.
But because I have these multiple iterators, instead of it being...
So normally it's XSS.Map...
Oh, I don't need that anymore.
That's scull two.
So now I have xs.
And when I have this thing, because I
have the multiple iterators, this is actually xss.flatmap.
We'll talk about that in a bit, but I want to illustrate what is going on here.
xs, not map, x. And then it's yielding x and xs dot length. So when I say this is syntactic
sugar, you can always take this for expression and convert it into something like that. Now
because you have the multiple iterators, you're getting a flat map followed by a map.
So we'll see the flat map in a little bit.
But this is interesting, because last week, and I'm going to take a little detour.
If we go to last week's homework, a student had a question about Exercise 3.
and that student had written.. Oh that's the solution, so let's go back to the other one.
So the student had written something like this and this is for do, so this is not a map,
This is a for each because it's for do.
But the student had written that.
And so what they actually were getting, and these are arrays.
They're not lists, but like I said, these functional programming methods are implemented
on all kinds of data structures.
So arrays are just another data structure.
So what we have is this same idea.
In this case, we were getting matrix.
matrix.flatmap.
And then we have row.
And then we had row dot nap.
Sell.
And then we have this do.
And so actually, to be correct, we should actually use for each.
I do this all the time.
I type the wrong one, and then I have to go back for each,
and then row for each.
So it's for do.
So then there was the rest of this, whatever had been in there.
And the test was failing.
and anyway you were getting something different than you thought you were
getting because this is dependent on that. So I corrected this by saying that you
had to actually do this...
You have to add this do here, and then a new for.
And then I think that's did there.
So now that we're not gonna run it because I didn't test this out.
But in this case, we still have the forEach.
I think in this case we have this nested matrix forEach.
This one's different because it's not map, but this is fundamentally going to give you
something different.
So let me get g, I have to look at this row and then, I guess I'm writing the same thing.
So now I'm confused.
then we had .
So I think because this is for each,
the distinction sort of goes away,
but what actually gets invoked for each is slightly different.
Anyway, I wanted to point this out.
Because these slides, if you're doing map for sure,
you're going to get something different.
You're going to get something different.
think I have to think about that. I will, if I, it's gonna bother me. So what I'm gonna do is I'm
gonna think about it later and I'm gonna put it in this one, okay? So we'll come back to that.
I thought I had something good there. I also thought I ended up with people asking questions
on the break, which is great because people are engaged. So I didn't have as much time to
get my thoughts in order. So I'll take a look at that and see if I can figure that out,
what I was trying to say. But this is going to be different than
with map, for sure. Because if you were doing this with map,
if this were map, so if this were
it just occurred to me
instead of for each, if you were doing
map
Oh, now I know what it is.
Okay, let's start it.
Sorry, it just dawned on me what I was doing wrong.
Okay, so yes, I apologize.
Let's start that again.
So with that version, or with what the student had actually,
it was the other way.
So let me back that out.
Live demos.
So what the student had was this.
And what that was was matrix.map, I believe, row, and then row.
Where's the do?
The do is out there.
So that would be the for each.
And this would be the math.
Pretty sure of that.
I'll double check on this.
But that's self.
So that's what you got when you did this.
So when you're doing for do, though, you generally don't do that.
we do separate do's, anyway, okay.
Lots of subtle details.
And most of the time I just use four comprehensions
because they're easier to reason about.
Alright, so there's multiple iterators.
Now, we have a cross product of independent iterators.
So in this case we have this four, right?
This is also going to be 1 to 7.
It'll be converted.
It's a range.
But it'll be converted to a, this part will be converted to a flat map.
And then this will be converted to a map.
And then we'll get this yield here.
So what's going on here?
So if I have XS, this is 11, 21, 31.
And YS is a list of A and B.
I'm going to end up with each element of the first list paired with each element of the second list.
That's what I'm going to get here, so you see 11 shows up with A and B,
and then 21 shows up with A and B, and then 31 shows up with A and B.
Now if I do this 1 to 7 and 1 to 9 and I yield this tuple here,
I'm gonna get 63 because I have 7 times 9 so it's the cross product and they're
independent so what we had here was these are deep end right because Xs came
from this expression here.
Okay, so...
What are our types?
So xs is obviously a list of ints, right?
ys is a list of strings.
Scala infers types for iterator variables, so x is gonna be what?
and y's gonna be string.
Good call.
I didn't realize it was all gonna come up with one bullet, okay?
Yield provides the type for the result, so what's the result?
It's this two tuple, right?
And the types are int and string.
So we're gonna have the type of the whole expression,
it's gonna be a list of tuples,
where the first element is an int, and the second element is a string.
So here's our summary.
Element-wise list processing is a universal higher order function.
So earlier I talked about higher level languages.
Now I'm talking about higher order programming, which is functional programming,
where you have functions involved.
When we call map, there's no flat map yet, but when we call map, we're passing a function.
So higher order functions.
Element processing function is provided as an argument.
The function is provided as an argument.
FOREACH is going to visit every element, map is going to create a transformed copy,
and filter is going to create a filtered copy.
Lists comprehension, so the syntax mimics loops for expressing lists comprehension.
So it's like a for loop.
It looks like a for loop in another language, but it's syntactic sugar for map and flat
map and with filter, or and filter, sorry.
for do, mimics for each, for yield mimics map, for, and then if there's an if in there,
it's going to mimic filter plus map.
Okay, so what does f do here?
Here's our friend, we've seen this before.
What is that?
Expend.
Compend, right?
Or append, I think we called it but same idea,
you're taking two lists and you're concatenating them together.
Okay, so we have a list of one element.
What's its type?
Not the type-
X.
The type of the Y, right, is X.
Okay, good.
And then what's the type of when we call F on the tail?
List of X.
So we have a list of X appended to a list containing just the element that was at the head here.
So what does this do?
Reverse.
Reverse is the list.
Yes.
Did everybody see that?
So if I call F of nil, we can actually break it down.
F of nil is going to give us what?
Which case is going to match, the first case, right?
So nil, you're starting to see that.
Okay, so we get a nil.
F of three nil is going to give us what?
List of three, not just three, not three,
but a list of three.
We have to be, in computer science,
we have to be precise with our language.
What about this one, f . What do we get?
List of 3 and 2.
List of 3 and 2, okay, good.
So this is reverse.
f should give us 3, 2, 1, and so on.
So f is reverse.
Okay.
Appending lists.
So, here's an append function, our type parameter is X, we take a list of X and another list
of X.
And we're going to look at XS, we're going to look at the first list, and we're going
to see if we have an empty list, we're just going to return the other list.
And if not, we have something with a head followed by, so this is only in the X side
now, followed by some other tail.
So we're going to keep the head and append it to the result of calling append on the
rest of x, and we're just going to keep on passing y down until we get to the other
point.
So, append 1, 2, nil, 3, nil.
So if I do that, I should get, let's see, so this is the first list, and that's the
second list.
And what it's showing is it's doing one, so it's hitting this case, one cons with this
recursive column, whatever the result of the recursive column was.
So we're appending, then we've got the rest of this list 2-0, and then 3-0 just gets passed
on down.
So now we're in here and we're gonna take that 2 off the head here and we're gonna append
to we're going to cons it with the result of calling append.
I've got to be careful with what I say, with the way I say that.
We're going to cons it with the result of calling append.
Now we're left with nil here, and we have 3 nil.
So when we hit the nil case, we'll just return ys, right?
So that's this 3 nil.
So that's why this collapses into 3 nil.
So.
We created new elements 1 and 2.
These are copies because we're doing call by value.
We're passing something in.
We'll talk about call by value later,
but we're passing one into actually,
well, it's copying the list.
That's the thing that's copied,
not the elements.
Sorry. It's saying new elements
1 and 2 are created,
but they're created,
but they're using the values that we got.
But, what's interesting here is this three nil
is gonna be reused.
So, we get all the way to the end,
we never deconstruct this thing, right?
So, we're gonna reuse that.
And actually what happens with lists,
so this is a feature of,
this is the nice thing about immutability,
if we have a list,
we're gonna draw the old data structure.
I'm just going to call this null instead of null.
But if we have this list and we're in this case here, we're just going to return this
thing and when we do that prepend or cons on the next one, we're going to then reuse
that one.
That's what's actually happening in memory.
We're reusing this.
So, I gotta be careful because it's not really,
these are ints so it's not really passing an int anywhere,
it's just we're using the same int that we have before.
But in Java, those end up being,
because we're running on JVM,
those end up being copied around in memory.
That's really low level.
So we have a new list, but the second part is share.
And as we build these lists,
and keep reusing.
So the list class has this built-in method.
This is our append.
Did we see this in another lecture?
I feel like we did.
Maybe.
Or am I just getting confused because I've taught this too many times?
That's possible, too.
So this built-in 3 colon is the append method.
So if I have 1 to 5 and 10 to 15, and I do this,
I'm gonna end up with this big long list which has 1 to 5 and 10 to 15 all
smushed into one list, flattened into one list, if you will.
So let's revisit the copy operation. So if I have copy here and I match with if I
have nil, then I just return nil. And if I have something else, I'm gonna take that
something else, and I'm gonna head of that something else and con it with
the result, calling copy recursively on the rest of the list. So if I do this,
copy, I'll end up with a copy of this thing. So if I started with 11-21-31, an
empty list and then a list of 4151, I get the same thing, meaning the value of
of this list if you looked at all the elements they would be the same but it's
actually going to construct a completely different copy of the list.
If I want to create a copy with a flat structure, so if we look at this one here
you see how we have this list of lists, sort of nested lists, but if I want to
create a copy with the flattened structure notice that copy is using
this cons operator.
So if I change
the implementation,
and notice the name will change to flatten,
but the implementation
changes
to use the append function.
So by doing that, I end up with
one list of x.
Notice the return types change too.
So here I had, over here, a list of
lists of x, right?
Now I have a list of x.
So I have this flattened list.
So that's what flatten does.
And now, what I was getting at before on the board and looking at the homework,
now we're going to look at what is flatten now, right?
So we know about map now.
We know that if we have, this is what our, if in this case, this is what our map looks like,
if we are mapping each element of our list to a list of y.
Instead of a y now, we have a list of y.
So this is the same outer type as this return thing.
So we take our xs, we match it.
If we get nil, well, we just return nil again, like usual.
Again, we have something else, and we have a head with some tail.
So what we're going to do is we're going to say,
if I call f of y and I cons it with the result of calling map,
The result of calling map is going to be a list of list of y.
So I also have f of y gives me a list of list of y.
So that's why I get that nested lists, right?
Now we're going to change it and we're going to transform the list,
but we're going to transform it differently.
We're going to flatten the structure.
We're going to have flat map.
So instead of flatten like we did before,
now we're going to flat map.
And with flatMap, notice the return type changed.
This is not a nested list of lists of things, it's now a list of y.
But this parameter hasn't changed, this function is still taking an x and
returning a list of y.
And notice the operator here is the append, instead of the comments.
So this will give us that flattened list that we want.
So that's why when you have the nested four like that, not the nested separate fours,
but when you have the multiple iterators.
That's why it has to be flat map and then map, because what it yields is a flattened structure.
I guess I said that backwards, the language uses that as syntactic sugar for the flat map,
and then followed that map.
So if you have multiple, like if you have four, X in XS, Y in YS, and Z in ZS,
then what you actually have is XS.map, and then you have YS dot, oh, I should have put it on your line.
Xs.map .
Because they're nested like that...
Xs.flatmap.
I always forget, because the last one and then zs.map.
The last one is the one with the map.
These are flat.
So when you have those nested things,
It's not backwards.
Okay.
So,
that's what flat map looks like.
So, the argument and return types of map and flat map.
So, map,
if we're going to do this,
each element of the result list is a list of y.
The length of the result is the length of xs.
So, whatever list we got,
If we've got five elements and we call this function on each of those elements,
we end up with five elements, but those elements are list of y.
And they can be whatever.
In flat map, we have the same thing here, list of x, and then a function here.
And this time we get a list of y, and each element of the result list is a y.
And the length of the result is the sum of the lengths of each of those inner lists
that we have in this version with the map.
So if I did this, xss.flatmap, this is actually, in Scala there's something called identity.
And the identity function is exactly that.
It just takes x and returns itself.
So if I flat map using the identity, flat map over the identity,
this is the same as just calling xss.flat.
If I did that in a for comprehension, for x and xss, and
then x and xss yield x.
So this is going to be a flat map and this is going to be a map.
I just have to look it up.
Which one is it?
Oh yeah, it's flat map, flat map, flat map and map.
Now wait you get the flat map.
So you can.
All right.
So now, those are functions on lists.
Now, we'll talk about methods and functions and this concept called curry.
And this is, this comes from Haskell Curry, who was that computer science guy.
Maybe it's mathematician, I don't know.
So how are methods, so an object-oriented program,
we have methods like on our classes, right?
So how are these methods related to functions in functional programming?
So we'll talk about the difference between methods and functions in Scala.
We'll identify the difference between tupled and curried functions.
So we'll talk about curried and what that means.
And then we'll talk about something called partial function
application, which is very useful in functional programming.
So here's some definitions.
We say that functions are first class
if they can be declared within any scope,
passed as arguments to other functions,
and returned as results of functions.
So, functions are this higher order concept.
So we've seen for each map and filter,
those are higher order functions
because they take functions as arguments.
You can also have functional programming
if you return a function as a return to it.
Return the function as a result.
I knew it was the right.
Okay, so this is how we're used to seeing methods
like when we've done things in Java and C, we have this argument list where we have x and y for our add function.
And if we call 11, I'm sorry, add with 11 and 21, this is what we call a tupled argument list.
So this is the usual style of methods that take multiple arguments.
So it's a method that takes a pair of ints, takes x and y and returns an int.
I actually wouldn't say that, I would say it takes two ints and returns an int.
But usually when I think of a pair of ints I think of a tuple.
So you can actually change this to actually have a tuple of x and y.
That's one parameter, but it takes two ints.
So that just shows you what happens when you call that,
in the REPL. So Scala has first-class support for both functions and methods. So here's a
method, keyword here is def, for defining a method. And we've seen that. And then over
here we have a function. This is, we're defining something called val, I'm sorry, something
called add, which is a value. That value has type. Oh, sorry. That value takes an argument
of a tuple, so we have an x and a y in a tuple, and produces the sum of that. So the type
of this val is going to end up being what? What do you think? Anybody? It's got to do
some kind of interpolation here, right? I'm sorry, inference is the word. It's got to
do inference. I'll do all the bullet points in a second. Well, so this is going to be
going to be a function. The type of add is going to be a function that takes a
tuple of two ints and returns it. So you have to learn to read this, okay? So it's
not hard if you look at what you see here and say, oh I'm getting a tuple of
two ints and I'm getting back an int. So the type of add has to be that and if I
put that in the REPL that's what you'll see. So these bullet points here, so
methods are part of a class structure, right? So we're used to that, we're used
to defining methods in Java. They can be overridden, so there's that whole like
type hierarchy thing, you can override things and it has access to fields that
are part of the class, right? So you have fields or instance variables that are
memory that are, that's allocated as part of an instance of a class. In a function,
we can pass functions as arguments, we can return functions, and we can assign them to variables.
So this is why this is a val.
When I see val, that means I have a value variable, which is an immutable variable.
And I can actually use that and pass that.
So here's function notation.
So this is a lambda notation.
We can also drop the x and y and use the whatever don't care idea.
So I don't really need to bind to variables.
I can just say, oh, I'm just going to take the first.
Scala will do this.
The compiler will do this thing, which will say, oh, I got two arguments.
That's the first argument.
That's the second argument.
So to use it, throw it away.
So the types can be inferred in some context.
So in this case, if I say that my add here is, and that's interesting that that's suddenly
a bar, that might be a typo, because that's a battle there.
what I'm doing here is I'm asserting, okay, add has to be this type. So this is the tuple of
int, int producing an int, right? So now the compiler knows that. It knows that this must
be an int and this must be an int. And then the result here, when I take an int and I add it to
another int, I get an int. So that's why the result here is int. So you can infer the type
sometimes. So now, we are going to change up our add and do something a little different.
So on the previous version, we had this thing where we had the two parameters. And now we
are going to have two parameters as well, but we are going to add the extra arrow. So
So now when I call this, instead of 1, the open paren, and 11, 21,
like before, now we have a single argument going
in the first parameter list and then another argument
going in the second parameter list.
So this is called a curried function.
And that's a function that, in this case,
it's a function that takes an int.
So add takes an int, and it returns a function.
See, on the right of the arrow, there is a function that takes an int and returns an int.
So you have to start kind of deconstructing these in your mind.
So this word curried is linked here.
So let's see.
Currying.
So in mathematics and computer science, currying is the technique of translating a function
that takes multiple arguments into a sequence of families of functions, each taking a single argument.
So the key here is that you have single arguments.
So add is a function that takes one argument and produces a function.
And what I did here was I called add, got my function back,
and then called that new function I got back by passing this other argument, 21.
And then that function will produce x plus y.
So if you do this in the REPL,
you're gonna get this like lambda stuff,
that's because it's constructing this thing called the lambda
and lambda has a two string method
and a two string method it's gonna print that out.
So that's why it's printing on the screen.
But if I call add 1121 here,
I'm gonna end up getting a result of 32.
So really all that's changing is before we had one argument
list and we were producing a result.
Now we have an argument that produces,
an argument to the function
and the function produces another function.
You can do this with methods too.
So with methods, if I want to do that,
my add method takes an int and produces a function
that this function I get back,
takes an int and produces another.
So you can mix the notations.
And so the difference here is that's a function and this is a method.
But what's interesting is the thing it returns is a function because of that notation.
So whenever you see the arrow, you're getting a function.
The arrow with the equal sign.
So if I want to convert methods to functions, I can do that.
If I have this tuple version and I say,
I'm going to do add and then underscore,
what this is actually doing is an anonymous function expression.
And it's saying that my add f is going to be add with the first.
Whatever I pass to add f is going to go into x.
And then it has to take y separately.
So on the right we see add is a function that x, y produces an int.
Here we have addf, this takes int int and produces and,
I'm sorry, this addf takes a tuple int int and produces an int and
and produces an int, and then its implementation is represented by this lambda expression.
Scala just prints out like that on the screen.
So then I can do something called partial application.
So if I have my addf that looks like that, so
it's a function that takes an int and returns a function that also,
So in turn takes a minute and produces a hint.
I can also do add M for methods, that's why that's method.
Add Fp, if I call add F with 11,
it'll slot 11 in there and that'll bind 11 to x and
then it will return this other function that takes this y thing.
So I can then later on called add Fp with 21 and
my RF will end up being 32.
And addmp will do the same thing, so if I call addmp 11, 11 will be bound to X and
then it will return back a function, that's what you see here, returning back a function.
So when you read these, you have to look for the colon,
this is the type of this thing, and then the equal sign means that this is what the implementation is.
So that's how you learn how to read these.
So again, partial application.
What we're doing is we're calling this thing with one of the arguments and we partially
applied it because there's still more work to do to execute the whole thing.
So we get back a function here that we can now pass the next argument.
So you can do that and you can reuse it.
So def defines a method with explicit parameter types.
This arrow thing defines a function with inferable parameter types.
Functions end up being objects with a method apply.
So this is what actually happens under the covers.
I have a function that takes an x and produces a y.
And in Scala, if I'm going to do this, I have to implement function is a trait that has an apply method on it.
And notice I have type parameters, so the trait says I have to implement an apply that takes something of type X and produces something of type Y.
So you might actually be able to put the word override here because it's defined in function.
So you'd have to put some implementation here.
So what the compiler does, functions are objects with method apply.
So what the compiler does is it's going to construct an object, construct a class actually,
and then when you run, when you use it, it's going to construct an instance of that class.
So function application e.args is method invocation e.apply.
So this is Scala syntax.
If I see this, there must be an apply method somewhere.
If I see this on something like this,
I guess I should say that if I have something defined like this
and I call that, I'm getting an apply.
Whereas if I just define a def or a val function,
there may not be an actual apply.
If there's a val, it will compile to this,
so there will be an actual apply.
It's in that val case that it does that.
If it's deaf, I think it's more like first class, automatically.
So here's our summary.
So we talked about two-pulled definitions.
That's the kinds of functions and methods we're used to seeing with multiple arguments.
Curry definitions are a family of single-argument functions,
so that's why we have a separate parameter list.
Now, I will say Scala will let you do multiple parameter lists with multiple arguments in each parameter list.
The reason it supports that, though, is because when you go toward pure functional, you start to have single argument functions.
So the Scala language itself doesn't require you to be purely functional in everything you're doing.
So you can have, like, you can have this.
You can have this where you have two argument lists, or an argument list, however many you
on and some number of parameters defined in here, that's perfectly valid in Scala.
But the reason why we have this in the language is so we can push toward single argument list.
So what I'm trying to say is having single argument list is not required.
When you do multiple, sorry, having single arguments in argument lists.
well, so it's not required, but for what we saw for
curried functions, and specifically for curried functions,
when you say that you're using currying,
you are using single arguments within each argument list.
So that's the distinction.
So in Scala, functions are objects with an apply method,
and partial application will create new functions.
Here's some examples of partial application.
So, add one, add two.
So, in add one, we have two arguments.
In add two, we have two argument lists.
This is a Curried version.
In add three, these are vowels,
so these are defs and these are vowels.
Here's add four,
which is a vowel that has this style here,
and then we have an add five,
which is slightly different.
But they're all gonna do ultimately the same thing.
So then these Ps, when you see these on this slide,
These Ps are for partial application.
So would add five still be curried?
What would that be?
What's your question?
Should it be?
Curried function?
Curried.
Add five is, yes, that's curried because it's
a single argument.
So all of the ones on here that have single arguments
are curried.
So what this is pointing out though, if I have functions like this defined, like add1,
see how there's different ways to do it, you can actually get partial application by doing
this underscore here. So syntactically, that will get you partial application. You can do that here
as well. This is with the multiple parameter lists, the current version. Add3P, we're back
to the case where we need to put the underscore here. Add 4p. In this case, because this thing
returns a function, you can take this function back and you don't have to do the underscore
thing. That's what's going on there. So if I have this code here, so actually this will
like... Oh, it doesn't show you everything. Okay. So if I do this... Oh yeah, it's all
over there. Okay, so if I have my list of... Here's my... This is actually a list of functions,
Right. So I have a list of add 1 P. Add 2 P. Add 3 P. Add 4 P. Add 5 P.
Each of these is going to be a function. Right.
So this will actually call apply on that function.
It will apply the function. That's why it's called apply.
Because we're applying a function. That's what we, that's how we say it in math.
So we're going to say, all right, I'm going to call f of 21.
So in each case of, you know, you can see it's pretty trivial.
It's always going to take whatever argument and add to 11. Right.
So that's why if we take this list of functions and then we map, because that's what this for yield is doing.
We map to calling f, we're going to get 32 for each one.
So that's kind of a summary of partial application.
That's the .
Okay.
And now we get into one of my favorite topics, folds.
And next week I'll tell you a little bit about my own learning journey with folds, because
for a long time in Scala I was like, what's the big deal with folds?
Next week I'll start with the first lecture slide deck will be how I learned all about
like strictness and non-strictness
and how they apply to folds
and how we can actually make better folds
than we get from the Scala collections out of the box.
So we'll do that next week.
But first let's talk about folds.
What are they?
How do we combine collection elements
into an aggregate result?
So that's what we've been doing right?
With our maps, right?
Our flat maps.
like, now we're going to start expressing result aggregation
using this new thing called a fold.
And we'll talk about the difference between fold left
and fold right.
So these are common concepts in functional programming.
All right, so here's a little exercise.
So we'll express this by iterating through the list.
In Java, we would do that something like this.
We have some mutable memory.
So again, our computation is stored here in this result
variable.
And then we iterate through the elements,
and we add each element to the result.
So that's the classic way we do sum.
In Scala, this is the Scala version of that.
Notice it adds this little ensuring contract here.
So we don't have this filled in.
So these three question marks if you haven't figured out yet
through not implemented error, I think I said that before.
But if you get your homework,
it all has these little bombs waiting for you to like,
they're not literal bombs, but they're like,
you know, it throws an all pointer exception,
so they're waiting for you to clean those up.
So, yeah, so here it's the same idea.
You'll have this mutable storage result,
and then you're always adding each X
to that result. This is a for do, so that's going to do a for each.
We want a concise function to aggregate all of the elements of xs into a single result.
We can express this with a recursive function. This is what your homework was last week,
So, if I'm calling sum, and I get to the end of the list, well,
the sum of that is 0, because that's the additive identity.
And otherwise, I have some head value and some rest of the list.
So, I take that head value, and
I add it to the sum of the rest of the list, right?
So, I just recurse on down, and if I do this, I end up with 63, I think.
I think. So this is how the computation proceeds. I call sum with the list. I pulled that 11 off and
I do 11 plus. I've seen this before. And then next time through, I pull the 21 off and I do this sum
and then I pulled 31 off and I do this sum. And I get to the end, I get sum of nil. That's going
going to be 0, so then I evaluate as the call stack exits and each function exits.
I end up with 63.
Oh, I can do math.
What about if we want to use a different 0 element?
So maybe, so this, I told you this last week, I think, or another week, that this kind of
syntax here means if I call the sum function without passing the second argument, it will
default the value to whatever I give it. So here when I call sum with excess, the second
argument is zero because that's the default value. So here I have my excess. When I get
to the empty list, I just take z, whatever z is. So if I'd called it with a thousand,
then I would have sum the list but added 1,000 instead of 0.
So that would be...it would be weird to do that because you wouldn't really maybe want that.
You wouldn't want to call that sum, might want to call it special sum.
I don't know what you want to call that.
But so it's a little interesting.
But again, this is somewhat contrived.
But that's...you can do that with a 0 element.
So if I call some 11 21 31 and get an empty list, then here I start with, I'm sorry, I
end with an empty list.
I don't get an empty list, I end with an empty list.
So I kind of pull this 11 off and then I call recursively, pull the 21 off, call recursively,
pull the 31 off, call recursively.
Now I get down to here.
So again, I'm going to get 63.
This is the same as before, but the only difference is I added a different 0 element, so before
I had hardcoded 0 on line 2.
So now I'm going to take that idea because that's kind of useless in and of itself but
I'm going to actually use that to my advantage.
This is touching on Raven's question from earlier.
This is tail recursive because there's no work to do here.
We're actually pushing the state down here into the parameters.
So in this case, when I have empty list, I just return whatever my z is.
Here what I'm doing is I'm actually doing the addition here before I call recursively.
So I'm gonna end up with, so this actually makes the z somewhat more compelling,
the accumulator idea.
So if I call this, notice now what's different,
before we had the 11 out here with a plus, right?
Now we have the 11 here.
So this is why there's no more computation to do over here.
So then now I've added 21 to 11 and passed it on down, right?
So now I'm at 32.
And now I'm adding 31 to 32 and passing it on down to 63.
Now I match on the nil case, so then the 0 element is 63.
And so it has these extra lines here.
That's just because the other one, it had extra spaces, right?
So it's just to keep it lined up.
I don't know why.
As soon as I saw that, I knew why.
But I was like, that's weird.
I didn't say this.
You can just imagine those three lines out there.
So that's like where it gets to the nil case
and immediately returns 60.
So this is, you know, the computer scientist will call this,
will say that you're summing the elements in a list
by computing forward.
You're computing forward because you're doing this computation
and then moving forward.
I cover this a little bit in Data Structures.
Although I never learned that in school.
So like this computing forward and computing backwards.
Although this is what they use in the literature
when they talk about programming languages
in the academic papers and stuff.
So now we're going to generalize the plus operation.
So we have this sum here.
This is pretty much what we've been doing.
We have our xs.
We match it.
We get nil.
We return the z. Otherwise, we take x, add it to the z,
and pass it on down as our new z to our recursive call.
We're going to generalize the plus operation.
And now instead, so see what we did here is we still have our xs list of int.
We still have our z, which is an int.
I'm going back and forth, by the way.
The function name is changing from sum to fold left.
Just look at the top line.
The word sum is changing to fold left.
And then we're adding a new parameter.
The new parameter we're adding is whatever the operation is.
So in this case, we have two ints that we combine somehow to produce a new int.
So we're generalizing the addition operation by passing that in.
We're abstracting out what the actual operation is.
So instead of sum, which implies that we're actually hard-coding the sum,
now what we're doing is we're saying,
I'm going to abstract that out. I'm going to take that sum and I'm going to make that something that the caller passes in.
So now this is why it's no longer called sum, it's called fold left.
Why is it called fold left? Well, think about what happens.
So if we get to the empty list, obviously we return whatever the Z is.
Otherwise, we combine the first element, the head,
with whatever the z we started with was.
And then that new result is passed down to the next recursive call.
And of course, we always have to pass the function down
because as we call recursively, we have to have access to that function.
So that has to be on the parameter list.
But now we're going to process the rest of the list.
So, notice what we are doing is, we are taking the elements from the left and doing the combination with the Z before recursing.
So that's why it's called fold left. We're folding from the left.
So if you memorize one thing, it's fold left means fold from the left and fold right means fold from the right. We'll talk about that later.
So, this will give us the same result with sum of 63.
So, what we've just done is we've implemented sum using bold left.
Now, what I did here was I changed the elements and aggregate type.
So, here, I was always dealing with ints.
I had a list of ints.
I had a z that was an int.
I had a function that took two ints and returned an int.
If I want my final result, which is over here, to be a string, for example,
then the types need to change.
So let's do that.
We just change this to a string.
But that means that our z, we have to start off with a string
because we have to combine whatever that string was
with whatever the next element is.
So we have to take the string and the int and produce a string.
So all I've done here, if you just look at the top line,
is I've changed all of these places that have string now.
They used to have int.
Okay?
But the structure is the same, right?
So I do xs match.
If I get nil, I get the z.
If I have xs rest, then I'm going to do fold left on the rest of the list,
but before I call that, I'm going to actually combine my new element x with my z
to get a new string.
that would be passed here for the new Z.
And of course, I have to keep passing the function on down.
So here, this illustrates nicely
that if we make the Z element the exclamation point,
that's what this call is, so we have our list,
we have the exclamation point,
and then we do a string concatenation
where we take the string, and then a space,
and then we add the int over here.
This is actually going to end up being int.
It'll call to string for you.
Because we're folding from the left,
we end up with the exclamation point on the left.
So let's now abstract out the types.
So what do we do here?
Well, instead of ins and strings,
we had z's and X's, so here we're fixing those types to int and string. Here we're
saying okay caller you can use whatever type you want. So we say the zero
element is the result, whatever the type of the zero element is going to be the
type of the result of the call and then X is going to define the type of the
input elements in the list. So what we've done now is we've abstracted out
out the list is now a list of x's.
And our z is now whatever type we define.
But this has to conform.
So this z type has to be here.
And this x type has to be here.
And when the combined function executes,
it has to give us a new z.
So if we deconstruct this, so if we have an empty list,
we just return whatever our z was.
That's why this is z.
And then if we have anything else,
we call fold left recursively on the rest of the list.
But we do that only after we've combined our x with the z
to produce a new type z, capital z.
And of course passing the function.
So here is what it looks like.
If I do fold left like this, I get the same result
as I had before.
All I've done is I've changed the types here.
I made the types abstract in the function,
in the function definition.
So we have fold-left versus fold-right, so I mentioned fold-right before, here it is.
It's probably easiest to look at the result first, so when I had fold-left, my z element appeared
on the left. When I had fold-right, my z element appears on the right. So here we have the same z
element.
Well, why?
Well, let's think about it.
We're used to that one.
We've seen that before.
Let's take a look and dissect this one.
So, here again, we have z.
We get nil.
Okay.
Notice what happens here.
So, if we have something else, this is different from that.
Here we had, first we called f, and then we called fold left.
now we call fold right and we don't call f until after fold right returns and
this is perfectly valid according to the types we have declared right so we're
gonna process the rest of the list and we're going to push that zero element
all the way on down and then we won't combine it until we start returning back
So it's just switching the order that we're doing things.
So folds are built in lists, so Scala defines fold methods and they're curried, so this
is curried because notice we have one argument here and as much as this looks like it's a
complicated thing. It's just a function. So it's a function that takes this and
returns this, but that's just a single argument. It's a function. See, it's one
thing. So they're curry.
Okay, so this is kind of a pictorial way to think about it.
If I call fold left, I end up combining the Z element with the first element.
And whatever the result of that evaluation is gets combined with the second element.
And then whatever the result of that computation is gets combined with the third element.
With fold-right, it's the other way.
So I call f, I call f, I call f.
I have to call f on the third element first.
first, and then I get the results.
So actually, let me go back to fold right, the definition.
Oh, it's right up there, okay, right.
So I call f, and then I call f again.
I'm saying this backwards.
My brain is like, cuz it's appearing first, my brain is doing this wrong.
I'm calling fold right first.
And I combine, I go all the way down to the end of the list C,
and that's where I combine my initial z.
That's what I meant to say.
So this is happening on the other side.
Now the result of that computation gets combined with b.
The results of all of that gets combined with a, and
that's what you see f on the outside here.
You may have heard of reduce,
You may have heard of mapReduce in your past.
So with a fold, the user, the caller,
provides the initial z value, if you've been calling it z.
So here you see the first argument list has a single zero.
That's our z in this case.
So in this case, we're summing the elements of the list.
If we use reduce, we don't have that initial z element.
So it will actually just start from the first element of the collection.
So you're forced to keep the type the same.
So if this is a list of ints, you have to produce a single int.
Here you can change the type by using a different value.
So with a Fold, the result type may differ from the Collection element type with Reduce.
You're going to start from the first element, and you're going to have the same type as the Collection element type.
So if I want to change the result type, I can do that with a Fold, but I have to provide the initial value.
here I can change the result type with a map before reduce.
So, in order to do this I actually have to chain these together.
So if I want to do this, if I want to produce the same result, I actually have to map each
element to two-string.
I have to convert it to two-string first.
first. So I have to go through the whole list and pivot each int to a string. And then I
can do this reduce. And that will produce the string one two three, and then I can concatenate
that exclamation point with the result of that one two three result. So that's fold
Versus reduced.
So folds are universal.
I thought maybe I was going to get more on the right.
So I can use folds to do all these things.
I can sum the elements of the list using a fold.
I can compute the product.
I can actually do an OR.
I can do an AND.
These bother me.
OR and AND.
We talked a little bit about the short circuit evaluation earlier.
Can you see why those bother me?
You have to actually go through all of the things, all of the elements in a fold left
and a fold right using the Scala dimensions.
So like if you hit a false, but you have if you're doing an and you hit a false, you
still have to process all the other elements.
And that was, we'll talk more about that next week, but that was why I was like what's
the big deal with folds any gray.
That was the name of a talk I gave once.
And that is the topic of next week's lecture where
I describe how I figured out how using strictness and non-strictness
will make these actually more compelling.
So or an ant bother me.
Append, flatten, length.
You can do all these with folds.
Reverse, map, filter, and reduce.
So these are pretty standard functional programming concepts.
So here's our summary.
Folds are universal functions to combine list elements into an aggregate result.
So fold from the left with fold left,
zero element is combined with the head.
So if I call fold left, my a gets combined with my zero element.
And then I'll keep combining.
If fold right, my last element gets combined with the zero element,
and then I keep combining as I go back through the list.
So there's lots of examples.
There's this link here for a tutorial on the universality of folds.
and this is, I guess, a paper from the Journal of Functional Programming from July 1999, okay.
What do we do with exceptions when folding?
So, in this case, notice this syntax is a little, I've mentioned this before, this is,
Syntax is another way to do a tuple.
So if you see four arrow two,
that's really the same as
a tuple of four two.
I'm going to erase this.
So when you see this,
That's the same as this.
Just a different way, different syntax.
So this is a list of tuples, right?
So if I do this fold left,
what do you think I'm going to get?
Reading it there, what do you see?
What does it do?
Okay, so best way to do this is to get our definition of fold left and expand it.
So where's our definition of full-fleft?
There it is.
I'm going to steal it from that slide.
That's a little small.
Oh, I can't make it a pair.
All right.
So if I have that, and I have C, and I have C, I have C, so I have C, I have this.
x.
I have xs, which is a list of x and z.
It's going to be type c.
And then my F, this is the right version, let me just see.
Oh, this is a, yeah this is the wrong version.
So this is the version that takes the list as a parameter
and the version we're seeing here on the screen
is part of the list implementation.
So, maybe this is the wrong way to go.
But we can kind of look at the other definition.
I'm not going to write it on the board.
I thought that that would make it easier, but it's not going to make it easier.
So if we look at the definition, let's take the example.
So the example, that's probably better.
I'll take the list of 4-2.
And then 9-3.
And I call fold left.
0, and then I have... you can use braces, but you could also just use a colon. I'll do
a colon version, because that works too. And I say case. I have an accumulator, and we're
So we're pattern matching on the tuple, and it helps if I write it correctly.
I'm a pattern matching on the tuple so we have n and d.
And we say, you have the accumulator plus n,
no, trying it mathematically, n divided by d.
Okay, so if we think about this,
it's a little bit different because the only real difference,
let me see if I can get to that one.
It's a little bigger.
The only difference is that this excess
is not a parameter here.
It's just the list you're operating on.
But these cases still work, right?
So if you think about when we process this list,
we start off with a list of,
and I'm gonna draw it slightly differently.
Oh, sorry.
4,2.
And, nine, three, oh yeah, you can do this.
This is a slightly different notation.
No, right, so that's the end of the list, right?
So when I look at my fold left in the case where I have something, the second case x
double colon rest, that will end up being fold left.
And I have the rest of the list, so this is going to be 9, 3, 0.
That's the first argument.
And then I pass f of 4, 2.
So what is that?
So this is our function.
So this is a function and
we're basically going to do the division, right?
So, 4 divided by 2 is 2, so we're going to say,
hold left.
Oh yeah, f, so our f is the division, right, so 4 divided by 2 is 2.
Oh boy, I'm screwing the whole thing up.
I'm going to have to do this.
I'm going to have to do this with the correct definition of fold left because I think that's
what's throwing me off.
So think about it though.
Let's look at this kind of differently.
So just read the English.
It's this, I'm trying to do it like in detail because we have 20 minutes to kill, right?
So, so what's happening here?
So what's happening here is I'm taking each tuple, right?
And doing the division, right?
So notice I'm pattern matching here on the tuple, right?
So n and d, so I take n divided by d, right?
So 4 divided by 2 is 2, right?
And then I'm adding it to the accumulator.
So that's my function.
So when I do fold left, what's going to happen is it's going to expand all the way.
It's going to actually take the 4 divided by 2 and then the 9 divided by 3.
So I'm doing it all wrong over here because I'm going the wrong direction.
Forget this.
So how does it know that the accumulator is zero?
It starts off right there.
It's the first parameter.
Oh.
Okay.
It's going to pass something else, right?
But that's how it knows, because the programmer gave it to them.
So, the case ACCND, it knows it because of the order that you put them in, or something?
Yeah, so with FoldLeft, the definition is going to...
We're going to deep dive into this more next week.
With FoldLeft, though, the definition is going to have the accumulator on one side.
And I don't remember if this,
I believe this is the right one
because the accumulator ends up being on the left.
So what it's doing is it's saying,
what this syntax means is,
this is actually,
remember that fold left has two parameter lists.
One of them takes the z,
that's what the zero is.
The other is a function.
So this syntax here is a function.
So you're just saying case,
you've got to use case
because you're pattern matching.
It's trying to deconstruct this.
So my two arguments to my function are my accumulator,
which will appear on the left in my fold-left definition.
If you look at the definition of fold-left,
you'll see that the accumulator's on the left,
and then I've got this N and D here,
and it's gonna then combine N and, sorry,
it's gonna do this work with N and D,
and then combine it with the accumulator.
So again, with fold-left, it's gonna go from the left,
from the left side, right, and it's going to,
and this is where this does come in handy,
it's going to call fold left on the rest of the list
before doing any computation.
So if you read the English, though,
this is the sum of the divisions.
So basically, we got 4 divided by 2 and 9 divided by 3,
and go study and figure out what order it happens in, right?
I think it's going to be the 9 divided by 3 will happen first,
and then it will sum that with 0,
and then it will then combine the 3 that we got from that 1
and then combine it with that 4 divided by 2.
So then we'll get 5, right?
Okay, so this gets back to the point of this slide.
What happens when we get something like this?
Anybody want a hazard to guess?
Remember we're pattern matching, so this is a numerator and a denominator, so this ends
up being numerator, denominator, numerator, denominator, well I'll say that 20 times fast.
So what happens when I take this one?
You're gonna get an error.
I'm gonna get an error, right.
So Scala will throw an error, actually put in the REPL.
Scala will throw an error.
So what happens is, it will end up throwing an error when this whole thing is executing
and it won't do anything.
So we can actually, no, it's gonna be useful for me to go into the REPL.
So here's our example.
And actually, I'm gonna illustrate it this way.
So I'm gonna call that I'm gonna now do something interesting.
Oops. It doesn't want me to do that. Okay. I want to insert a new line here.
It doesn't let me. Alright, I'm gonna type it. 4 arrow 2, 9 arrow, oh do I have to...
I think the spaces are fine. That's a habit. Arrow 3,
I'm gonna use call for the syntax.
eck, n d.
So this time, instead of just, oh wait, let me do that.
Okay, I'm gonna say...
I think you're missing a parenthesis with this.
parentheses like the case at the end?
You're right.
Thank you.
I'm actually just trying to print out some stuff
so we can see the order that it processes in.
Then I'm going to put the semicolon,
which is our sequencing operator.
I just don't want to put in a new line.
Now I'm going to say,
Now we'll see, when we do this, we'll see the order that it prints them in, right?
So it does process the four by two.
Oh, and maybe I'll change it to combining with...
Oh, yeah.
Combining with dollars.
Okay.
Let's do that.
Oops.
Sometimes it takes new lines, and sometimes it doesn't.
Oh!
Except, I have to remember the name of my parameter.
It's acc.
All right, let's try that.
So, four divided by two, all right, so I said it wrong.
This is what happens when I get confused, I say it wrong.
This is part of the reason I did this, was I wanted to actually add this print line,
show you like what order it prints it processes in so it's processing the 4 and the 2 first and
combining with 0 and then it's gonna process the 9 and 3 next and combine that with 2.
So that was what I was trying to do on the board when i started to draw it out i was going to draw
out the steps but i quickly got confused so this way the compiler backed me up and the
a REPL back me up for sure.
So, now what happens with this version?
So this is what I've been driving towards.
And Dylan correctly pointed out that we'll get an error.
So we get an arithmetic exception, divide by zero.
So, this is similar to that result that we saw earlier,
but it's slightly different.
This either thing is built into the language.
So what am I doing here?
I'm saying that my type for
the results is going to be in either a throwable,
which is super-type of exception, or an int.
So this is the case where I get a valid result.
This is the case where I encounter an error.
It's different from that result example from the quiz because we're not accumulating
here if we encounter one error, we're done, like we stop.
So here's my function that I passed to fold left.
Notice the z is now gonna be right of zero, so
an either is another algebraic data type.
And instead of, like in the result, you had an error or an okay,
in either you have a left or a right.
And the left can be of type trable,
and the right can be of type int.
This is also a summed.
So in my function here, I'm going
to call flat map on either.
We talked about flat map earlier,
but either have map and flat map implemented on them.
And I'm going to then take my A.
So where's, oh, A is the parameter right.
So my accumulator, A is what's stored in the right of the accumulator,
the right if there is a right accumulator.
So FlatMap is going to then try to do, to take right the zero value.
That's this.
That's A the first time.
It's gonna try to take zero and add it to the division,
the result of the division.
And if I get an error, I'm gonna catch an exception.
So we can use try catch syntax in Scala.
And I'm gonna wrap the exception in a left.
So that's where this throwable on the left side comes from.
So I can collect the first exception in either.
And once I get that, then it will still process each element.
Because this is still going to annoy me, because I'm going to have to call flat map on a left,
and if you call flat map on a left, you just get whatever the left is holding.
It doesn't do anything.
So, but you still have to go through and process it.
So we'll talk more about that next week.
All right.
So, sorry, I got a little bit off the rails today.
that's the thing, I prepped like last night for class
and I was like, on my lunch break, I was like checking today
and making sure I had all I had in my mouth, I screwed up.
So it happens, humans, we're fallible, we make mistakes.
But this introduces either, so go read up on that if you want.
I don't remember if we talked about that.
We'll talk about options.
options, these are similar to options where options are either no value or some value.
This is how you would hang on to if you got some kind of error.
You'd be able to hang on to that and report it.
So, have fun with folds.
And next week we'll talk more about folds.
That's it.
That's it. That's all I got.
Thank you.
Thanks, have a good week.
Thanks, everybody.
I'm going to hang up the Zoom now.
Talk soon.
Thank you.
Have a good week.
I'm not a good last two places.
So, thanks.
Thanks.
Thank you.
Have a good week.
Oh, okay.
Sure.
Welcome.
What's your name?
Yeah, I think you do.
Have a good night.
Thank you everyone.
See you later, take care.
Did it start raining?
I didn't check.
I forgot I was gonna do it last night.
on the border between Wisconsin and Illinois.
Yeah, and I was giving texts about...
...some like in like...
Metropolitan Water Reclamation District or something,
declaring a flood launch or whatever...
Tornado watch. It's gonna be a mess.
Yeah.
It seems like so far, it's still a little north of us.
Like in Evanston and Island Park.
There are some crazy supercells over Rockford right now.
At least some huge head.
So far it feels like I haven't been understanding folds better than last time.
Good. That's good.
But we shall see when I do the homework.
Well, do the homework and let me know if you have questions?
Yeah, we'll... I'll see you Tuesday.
Alright, see you next week.
so
Thank you.
Okay.
...
and after this video, it's going to be possible to play.
so
I'll see you next time.
Okay.
Thank you.